<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>My Experiments - life</title>
	<subtitle>My Blog and Projects</subtitle>
	<link href="https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/life/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://arunkd13.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/life/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Vacant Land Tax</title>
		<published>2024-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/vacant-land-tax/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/vacant-land-tax/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the year 2017, the Chennai Corporation (later called Greater Chennai
Corporation or GCC), started imposing a tax on vacant land within its
boundaries. This was to discourage land hoarders—and more importantly, to
increase their revenue.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple way to pass on generational wealth that was accessible to the common
man, became less economical. It might be justified if the government did a
better job of enforcing land grabbing laws in the city, but it is not the case.
Police for their part, in cahoots with the politicians impose their own tax.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vacant land tax seems to have been initiated by other urban bodies in Tamil
Nadu, and the other states too, around the same time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had inherited one such parcel of land in 2008 and had to pay my dues, before I
could exercise my rights to develop it. But as usual, this straight forward
task was made needlessly tedious, by our government officers and politicians,
and an opportunity for them to profit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chennai Corporation&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;gcc&#x2F;department&#x2F;revenue&#x2F;#revenue&quot;&gt;Revenue Department has very detailed information on
their website explaining all their procedures&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and the formula for calculating the vacant land tax. Along with the &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;departments&#x2F;revenue&#x2F;StreetRates&#x2F;Z-13%20STREETRATE.pdf&quot;&gt;Basic
Street Rate (BSR), for zone
13&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
I was able to get an idea of the tax I would have to pay.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found a document explaining the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;gcc&#x2F;SOP&#x2F;REVENUE_SOP.pdf&quot;&gt;SOP for all revenue department
procedures&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
another document giving the SOP specifically for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tnswp.com&#x2F;DIGIGOV&#x2F;StaticAttachment?AttachmentFileName=&#x2F;procedure&#x2F;pre_op&#x2F;PO_34.pdf&quot;&gt;new assessment of property
tax&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
The process for vacant land tax assessment was essentially the same as any
regular property tax assessment that you make for a built house or any other
structure.  The entire process had an SLA of 30 days. There was also &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;erp.chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;e-portal&#x2F;login.do&quot;&gt;a website
where an online application can be made for the
assessment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, in
addition to other services.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good, and I was happy with our Digital India!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I completed the form and tried to submit the application, and I got a 502
error—looks like our officials had managed to sabotage the online process. What
is advantageous for the citizen, is likely, not so for them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a paper form for new tax assessment that came up in search results,
but it had umpteen columns and details, that I decided to go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;mbHyH4KNGTREYzTt5&quot;&gt;zonal
office in Adyar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to enquire. I have
too many scars from my engineering college days, when highly educated lab staff
would throw my meticulously crafted record out, for not having used the same format
as my seniors. Yes, they too had a government job, and they knew it comes with
some perks—no one can take it away from them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Monday, I reached LB Road in Adyar and walked past a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Mahindra_Bolero&quot;&gt;Bolero&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Toyota_Fortuner&quot;&gt;Fortuner&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to enter into the
office on the ground floor. I grew an inch shorter as I realized, no one really
cared what entered their office. Everyone where busy with their &lt;em&gt;work&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I felt
like a ghost, or should I say, the invisible man?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I slowly assessed who might be least annoyed, when I disturb them. Sitting right
next to the entrance was a person, slightly older than me, looking busily at
some files—I decided he would be my best bet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, I want to enquire about vacant land tax...&amp;quot;, I said, approaching him. He
cut me off replying, &amp;quot;Give the letter to him&amp;quot;. He was pointing to the desk in
the centre of the room. There were a few people standing there and one of them
was doing all the talking. Happy that I did not take more of the officer&#x27;s
precious time, I approached the clerk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;No, no form. Just give a letter.&amp;quot;, he said. &amp;quot;Attach a copy of the sale deed and
patta. And don&#x27;t forget to attach the EC&amp;quot;. EC stood for Encumbrance Certificate,
a document that provides the list of transactions pertaining to a specific
survey number. Proud that I already knew that, I returned home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only then it struck me, that I did not know, whom the letter needs to be
addressed to. I went through the documents that I had, and the SOP mentioned the
&lt;em&gt;Assistant Revenue Officer&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in a number of places—I decided he was my man.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;request-for-property-tax-assessment.odt&quot;&gt;Here is the format of the letter I had
used&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, in case you find it useful. Use
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.libreoffice.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LibreOffice&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to open and edit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put all the documents in a green, cloth-lined envelope and carried an
additional copy of the letter that I could get dated, stamped and signed by the
clerk as an acknowledgement. This is the SOP that needs to be followed when
submitting documents to the government—I had learnt this from my father.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What Sir, should I do all the work? Take the letter out of the envelope and
give it to me. Write your name and phone number on the top&amp;quot;, said the letter
clerk when I gave it to him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, sure&amp;quot;, I removed the documents, underlined my name and phone number
that were already there on the letter and handed them to him. I was
proud of my forethought, &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter clerk duly dated, stamped and signed my acknowledgement copy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, when will it be ready?&amp;quot; I asked sheepishly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir is in a meeting. He will call you&amp;quot;, he replied. I glanced furtively at the
designation on the board outside Sir&#x27;s room. It said—Assistant Revenue Officer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After submitting the letter, I waited for 2 more weeks. I did not have much hope
for any SMS as mentioned in the SOP. But I wanted at least, half of the SLA to
be past, before I ask for the status—I didn&#x27;t want to annoy the officers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to the Zonal office once again and enquired with the letter clerk.  &amp;quot;Sir,
just left now. All the officers are having a meeting in the Ripon building. You
do one thing. Call this number. He is the assessor. He will tell you the
amount&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I called the assessor, and he asked to come by the local corporation office at
Brindavan Nagar Main Road the next day. When I reached there, only his assistant
was present.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What is the area?&amp;quot;, he grabbed the calculator lying on his desk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, tax will be for the entire 7 years&amp;quot;, he proceeded to calculate the amount
and pointed to the numbers that showed up on its liquid crystal display.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You have to give a DD for the amount. Only after you give the DD, we can enter
into the system. Call Sir.  He will tell you the correct amount.&amp;quot;, he concluded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thanked him and moved to a bench away from his desk and called the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Did you send the letter by post?&amp;quot;, he asked. &amp;quot;Ah… OK. I haven&#x27;t received the
documents yet from Adyar. I will call you once I get it.&amp;quot;, he said, ending the
call.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back home, nervously waiting for the call. The assessor called after a few
days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What is the plot number? Where does the Sri Krishna Nagar come?&amp;quot;, he asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, it is an unapproved layout and your department is no longer using the
original name.&amp;quot;, I replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;OK, can you submit a copy of the parent sale deed where the plot number is
mentioned?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes&amp;quot;, I replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after, I took the document copies to the Brindavan Nagar Main Road
office and gave it to the assistant. &amp;quot;Sir, is in Velachery office. I will give
it to him, when he comes by&amp;quot;, he said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some chit-chat, he hinted, &amp;quot;I don&#x27;t know when the assessor will come. If
you want, I can go and give the documents in Velachery today itself.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sensed in his voice, the hope of making a few hundred rupees to indulge in his
favourite vice. I was not going to fall for his sweet talk. &amp;quot;Sir said, he will
collect it when he comes by&amp;quot;, I replied firmly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• • •&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Your tax will be Rs. 23,200&amp;quot;, the assessor finally called around a week later,
quite late in the evening. &amp;quot;Bring a DD for the amount tomorrow.&amp;quot;, he reminded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the same amount that the clerk showed on the calculator. Until now, I
had not given any bribe to the assessor. Neither did he ask for it. I wanted to
see, how far I could hold.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, why did he ask for a DD? The SOP clearly said that the assessor would raise
the notice for tax with the bill number, and we could pay it through a number of
channels including, online payment or swipe a card at one of the ward offices.
The amount that I had to pay was significant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What if the assessor misused the DD or delayed the process after I give it to
him?&amp;quot;, I asked my mom in trepidation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Government officers will not do such things&amp;quot;, she assured.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounded very naive, but 35 years of experience in the education department
of the Tamil Nadu State Government, should count for something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;He will write your name and the bill number in the back of the DD&amp;quot;, she
assured. This sounded like a better advice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I will write my name myself&amp;quot;, I said, happy that the DD cannot be
misused to pay tax for someone else.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor could still, simply deny receiving the DD, while still raising the
bill. But this would only be an attempt to spite me, and he could not personally
profit from it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I decided to leave nothing to chance. &amp;quot;I will take a photo copy of the DD and
get it signed by the assessor as an acknowledgement&amp;quot;, I declared.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, I took the DD and hurried to the corporation office and
forgot to take a photo copy and also to write my details in the back of the DD.
How stupid of me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor took the DD, wrote my name and phone number in the back and put it
in his drawer. &amp;quot;The bill will be ready in a day or two. You will receive an SMS.
You can come and collect the receipt from the office.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not hint on any bribe, but his demeanour was cold and impersonal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still cursing myself for not having taken a photo copy and was a little
worried. But decided to leave it at this and call the assessor only after a
couple of days. Soon, I got busy with other work and on the second day, I got a
call from the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Your bill is ready. Collect it from the Velachery corporation office&amp;quot;, he said.
&amp;quot;Yes, it is near the Dhandeeswaram temple in Velachery.&amp;quot;, he further directed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was familiar with the place but never knew that a corporation office existed
there. I asked a local person on reaching the place, and he pointed to the
building, which is not easy to miss, once you start looking for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going inside the building, past the trees, I saw a typical government office,
with a building in faded yellow, or was it blue? I cannot remember. There was a
shed being repaired in the front.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor was sitting behind a counter with a computer. &amp;quot;This must be his
primary work location&amp;quot;, I said to myself. He was on the phone with someone, but
on seeing me, he printed a copy of the bill, stamped and signed it, while
still multitasking on the phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I missed adding the late fee. You need to pay that also&amp;quot;, he said after
finishing the phone call. It amounted to a few hundred rupees.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Can I pay it by cash?&amp;quot;, I asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There is no work for cash after this. Everything is online. If you have a card,
you can swipe in the machine here&amp;quot;, the assessor replied, pointing to the desk
by his side.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took out my debit card and gave it to his assistant who was at the swiping
machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling happy at the turn of events, I thanked the assistant and the assessor
for their work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;YOU COME AND GO SO MANY TIMES FOR THIS WORK, but you never think of giving us
something for our expenses. GIVE AT LEAST 1000 TO HIM&amp;quot;, the assessor finally
let his frustration out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was feeling ashamed on hearing it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked the person to come outside the office. There I took two Rs. 500 notes
and gave it to him. Emotions of shame, pity and thankfulness suppressed the
analytical side of my brain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• • •&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking through this episode now, I could have saved myself a lot of work and money
by going directly to the assessor, dropping the letter along with a Rs. 500
note, like a professional.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But would that improve things? No.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should still give the application in the Zonal office, where I get an
acknowledgement with the date of submission. It is likely that the SLA of 30
days is being tracked, which is why the assessor finished the work without me
pushing for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also insist on online transfer or card payment instead of the DD. Even
if it meant bribing the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if my mom is true, and government officers do not commit fraud, at least
for such small amounts, the DD business gives undue power to the officers in
addition to being cumbersome. All three must be put to an end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Trouble with Sarathi</title>
		<published>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/trouble-with-sarathi/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/trouble-with-sarathi/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had to renew my wife&#x27;s driving licence which was issued at Tindivanam RTO.
Unfortunately, it was not uploaded into the computerized records at the time it
was issued, and it was a prerequisite for renewing the licence from a different
RTO other than the one where it was issued.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On enquiring at a local driving school, they asked to visit the concerned RTO
and request them to upload the details into the system. Half done digitization,
and countless hours of human life wasted, with each person having to make a request
individually!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited the RTO in person and the letter receiving clerk asked to write a
letter as he is wont. Accepting the letter and a copy of the licence, he
dismissed me saying that I will receive an SMS in a week or so after it is
uploaded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never got any SMS even after 2 weeks. On checking the driving licence in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sarathi.parivahan.gov.in&#x2F;sarathiservice&#x2F;stateSelection.do&quot;&gt;Parivahan Sarathi portal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, it
showed an application number, and it was pending approval.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another visit to the RTO, this time, by my father-in-law and the answer was that
there was some delay in the server, and they would upload it in a few days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, I never received any SMS after that, and without a proper way of
knowing the status, I was resigned to have someone visit the RTO once again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to check the status one last time, before the imminent visit, but the
site was frustratingly slow. I even disabled &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;UBlock_Origin&quot;&gt;uBlock
Origin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
suspecting that some &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; bloatware was causing problems. But still the
website was slow. Finally, when I got to the view the status, it showed that the
application was blocked on me for uploading the required documents. When I tried
to upload them, it errored out and the site hanging on every step was
making it even more difficult to figure out why I got the error.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of frustration, I decided to dig a bit deeper into the site, and
opened the Web Developer Tools on Firefox. I was able to see calls to
&lt;em&gt;vani-hyd.nic.in&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; hanging and timing out after a few minutes—this was the
reason the website was slow. I also realized, this might not be a critical
part as, after time out I was able to proceed to further steps. On
right-clicking the URL in the request list, I noticed that there was an option
to block it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was exactly what I needed! I was excited by the possibility of me
finally completing my part of the application process—uploading the documents.
On finishing that step, it still errored. Cursing the software developers who built the
website, I began reading the page more attentively. Hidden in the verbiage of
instructions, it was mentioned that the file size should be less than 500 KB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick processing step with Ghostscript brought the file size down, within
limits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;gs -sDEVICE=pdfwrite -dCompatibilityLevel=1.4 -dPDFSETTINGS=&#x2F;ebook -dNOPAUSE -dQUIET -dBATCH -sOutputFile=output.pdf input.pdf
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was all smoothing sailing and the upload process succeeded, though it
abruptly landed on the initial status request page without any mention of the
happy news. I had to once again key the application number and the captcha to
find the updated status—further actions were on the RTO.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t think everyone would be able to complete this step without
seeking assistance from a third party like a driving school. Looks like Digital
India instead of improving things, has just added another layer of
private intermediaries between the government and the citizen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process took another 3 weeks, where my computer skills didn&#x27;t help, and my
father-in-law had to still visit the RTO to prod the officers into action. The
clerk was kind enough to give his phone number, so that, we could remind him
over the phone, instead of a direct visit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only nice part of the whole process was that, there was no direct ask for a
bribe to speed things up. The clerk and the officer were trying to genuinely
complete the process, though hampered by inefficient systems and their lack
of skill.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>@sunson</title>
		<published>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right from my school days when I started using the Internet, I had been
following people on the Internet, from whom I have continously learnt and shaped my
understanding of the world. Although it might sound a bit kitsch, I would compare this to the
relationship between &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Ekalavya&quot;&gt;Ekalavya and
Dronacharya&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but the comparison breaks
down when I gratefully recollect how much more I have received from my gurus than
what Ekalavya received from Dronacharya. And have I been as worthy a student as
Ekalavya? I don&#x27;t think so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these exemplary gurus and closest to my heart has been Suraj Kumar. I
remember, the first time I saw him was around 1998, in one of the ILUGC (Indian Linux User&#x27;s
Group - Chennai) meetings held regularly in the IIT Madras campus. He was the same age as
me, but vastly more knowledgeable and driven. I was this reticent Linux newbie
and was at
awe with the MoM&#x27;s he wrote after
each meeting - every detail captured in his pleasant style with a unique sense
of humour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued to follow his posts as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;@sunson on Live
Journal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;sunsonian&quot;&gt;@sunsonian on
Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The later half of the 2000s were the
heydays of Web 2.0 and
there were increasingly more options for staying connected and learning from my
gurus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I internalized a number of life changing concepts like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Peak_oil&quot;&gt;Peak
oil&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Emergence&quot;&gt;Emergence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; through his writings and
the links he posted on the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Delicious_(website)&quot;&gt;Delicious bookmarking
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. He introduced me to
other communities like &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;theoildrum.com&#x2F;special&#x2F;archives&quot;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
which opened their own wide worlds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I was already an atheist, @sunson&#x27;s explorations and thoughts were much
deeper. He introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Richard_Dawkins&quot;&gt;Richard
Dawkins&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and I devoured his
books, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_Selfish_Gene&quot;&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_God_Delusion&quot;&gt;The God Delusion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest impact he had on me must be his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;sunson&#x2F;albums&#x2F;72157626205527503&quot;&gt;efforts at natural
farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I
eagerly followed his journey as he introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Masanobu_Fukuoka&quot;&gt;Masanobu
Fukuoka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s writings and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;G._Nammalvar&quot;&gt;Nammalvar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This had a great impact on my own journey into natural farming that I
started in January 2022.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like everything ends where it starts and I learn &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.freelists.org&#x2F;post&#x2F;ilugc&#x2F;ILUGC-Trichy,6&quot;&gt;from this post on the ILUGC mailing
list&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that @sunson is no longer
with us. In this ephemeral digital
age, I am thankful that the Internet Archive&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Wayback_Machine&quot;&gt;Wayback
Machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.archive.org&#x2F;web&#x2F;20231204190058&#x2F;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Live Journal
blog
archived&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
although his delicious bookmarks and his personal website are lost. The Twitter
feed anf Flickr photos hang on a noose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope his writings survive the bitrot and continue to educate and
inspire more of us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Risk Disclosure on Derivatives</title>
		<published>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/disclosure/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/disclosure/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following disclosure was shown, when I logged into my ICICI Direct account. Usually I skip reading these disclaimers, but this time I took the time to read it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 out of 10 individual traders in equity Futures and Options Segment, incurred net losses.
On an average, loss makers registered net trading loss close to ₹ 50,000
Over and above the net trading losses incurred, loss makers expended an additional 28% of net trading losses as transaction costs.
Those making net trading profits, incurred between 15% to 50% of such profits as transaction cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: SEBI Study&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woah, this is pretty hard hitting. It is not just the loss makers who are losing money, but even the profit makers lose a major portion as transaction cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting that, this gets splattered all over the trading interface, like the smoking warning on cigarette packs, and yet, people continue to use them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Public Libraries in Chennai</title>
		<published>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/public-libraries-in-chennai/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/public-libraries-in-chennai/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Libraries have always been a place that excited me. They laid out the wonders of the world — past, present and future — in an all you can eat buffet. When I was a kid, I fancied myself starting a lending library and catalogued all the books in my house, but atleast, I ended up reading almost all of them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the distractions available to today&#x27;s kids, books are their least preferred form of entertainment. They do get books from the neighborhood lending library, but they seem to be atleast 5 years behind the kind of books that they should be reading for their age.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public libraries as a concept is very noble, but they may sound irrelevant when you can get almost the entire world&#x27;s knowledge on the Internet. But no ebook can beat the physical book in terms of the humane interface they provide and continue to be costly for a voracious reader. Public libraries make this luxury, something that everyone can enjoy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to visit they Public libraries in Chennai to see their state and make them one of the places that my kids go by themselves to in the City.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;district-central-library&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennai.tnlla.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;District Central Library&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first public library that I went to, as a kid, in the 1990s. It had atleast 3 floors of books, then, and also a kids section. Now when I visited it in 2023, it was reduced to just the ground floor and the place looks totally run-down. The books were dusty and the collection was very poor. Many books were also marked as reference only. Looked like the budget has been severly cut and &#x2F; or the books moved to other libraries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter this library and read books as a visitor. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. The membership cost is less than Rs. 100 per year and you can take 4 books for 2 weeks that you can extend twice or thrice over the phone. For membership, you just need to provide an identity proof and an address proof in Chennai. Aadhar card or driving license should work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find some books that interest you, this might still be worth a membership.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;EXJafR7pJFQ1e4yG9&quot;&gt;735, Anna Salai, Near TVS Bus Stop, Anna Salai, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600002&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Easily accessible from the Thousand Lights Metro station.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No usable online catalog&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;anna-centenary-library&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.annacentenarylibrary.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Anna Centenary Library&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is surely the biggest and the best public library in Chennai. Being the newest, the infrastructure is still very good. It supposedly has 9 floors, but I had time to visit only 3 floors. Surely a great collection of books neatly organized.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter the library and read books. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. Only downer was they refused to provide membership, although the website states the membership categories and fee details. This also being in south Chennai and without metro access, is not very convenient for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;jE5PmEGMsRkQSN2x8&quot;&gt;Gandhi Mandapam Road, Kotturpuram, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600085&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. No metro access&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;117.239.65.6:8001&#x2F;&quot;&gt;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;117.239.65.6:8001&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;connemara-public-library-chennai&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.connemarapubliclibrary.org&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;Connemara Public Library Chennai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is likely the oldest public library in Chennai, if not india. There were atleast 4 floors of books with a decent collection that are also available for lending. Overall this looked to be the best option for someone living in north Chennai.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can visit the library and read books. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. The membership requires you to be a resident of Chennai and also have the form attested by a gazetted officer or a notary public. A bit onerous but looks to be worth it. Books can be extended over the phone for conveninence. Cost should be less than Rs. 200 per year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;tRCR7fjs9ELcT9Yu8&quot;&gt;Pantheon Road, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600008&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Around 2 kms from Egmore metro station.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No usable online catalog&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-center-chennai&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;in.usembassy.gov&#x2F;education-culture&#x2F;american-spaces&#x2F;american-space-chennai&#x2F;&quot;&gt;American Center Chennai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the smallest library that I had visited and the books seemed to be only from US publishers. The collection looked to be irrelevant for someone in India. It would have been redeemed if there were more classics and best sellers from the US, but all the books and magazines seemed to be dated and obscure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter the library and read books. You need to bring a valid, original photo ID like a driving license, that should be submitted at the security check along with your mobile phone. The membership is very affordable, at Rs 400 per year. Might be worth to consult the online catalog and join for very specific books that might be available only there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;QTbbKc2xvRyFvoS37&quot;&gt;Next to Anna Flyover, Gopalapuram, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600086&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Around 1.5 kms from Thousand Lights metro station. Enterance is through the gate on the Catherdral road side.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;americanspacesindia.on.worldcat.org&#x2F;discovery&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;americanspacesindia.on.worldcat.org&#x2F;discovery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Fastag chargebacks</title>
		<published>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/chargebacks-on-fastag/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/chargebacks-on-fastag/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have got a couple of chargebacks for less than Rs. 200 on my ICICI Fastag account,
in the past few years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first one I totally panicked and raised a ticket
on the online portal which requested for the RC copy to be attached. It took
around a month for the amount to be returned back to my account.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time in Nov 2023, I got another chargeback, but I missed to raise
a ticket immediately. After a few weeks I got a message that my complaint on the
chargeback has been raised. I was perplexed and logged into my account to
look for any tickets that have been raised. And there it was, a ticket
raised in my account, with the RC copy being a screen shot of a Bihar
Transport department website, which allows to pull up RC details with
vehicle number.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if these are genuine faults in the system, but in any case,
I think allowing the company running the toll booth to both raise a
chargeback request and also automatically raising a ticket to dispute the
chargeback, is a process that can be easily abused. Since it takes more than
a month for the dispute to be resolved and money credited back to the
Fastag account, it can be used as operating cash by someone in the system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My guess is, this is likely the toll operators who are doing this. With a
trickle of chargebacks and resolutions after a month, this can be made
to look like genuine faults, but they benefit with a huge cash flow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably someone needs to file an RTI requesting for the details and also
if there are any penalties levied on the toll provider for incorrect 
chargebacks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching on the Internet, I found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.team-bhp.com&#x2F;forum&#x2F;street-experiences&#x2F;210138-raise-dispute-trip-new-trick-toll-plazas-cheat-fastag-users.html&quot;&gt;this thread on team-bhp.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
dating back to 2019 raising similar concerns. And another &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.moneylife.in&#x2F;article&#x2F;fastag-wrong-deductions-why-complaints-are-not-getting-resolved-sooner&#x2F;63149.html&quot;&gt;long wieldy article
on
moneylife.in&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
giving some data on chargebacks, but nothing that suggests a proper
resolution for this issue.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Check status of income tax refund</title>
		<published>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/income-tax-refund/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/income-tax-refund/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not sure if this is obscure, but I had to google to find out this page which
gives the status of income tax refund for each assessment year:
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tin.tin.nsdl.com&#x2F;oltas&#x2F;refund-status-pan.html&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tin.tin.nsdl.com&#x2F;oltas&#x2F;refund-status-pan.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
