<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>My Experiments - health</title>
	<subtitle>My Blog and Projects</subtitle>
	<link href="https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/health/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://arunkd13.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2024-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/health/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>No poo and some more</title>
		<published>2024-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/no-poo/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/no-poo/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started having excessive dandruff starting from my teen ages. The obvious solution at
that time was to switch from &lt;em&gt;Clinic Plus&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Head and Shoulders&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; for my weekly
hair wash, which we called, the head-bath. The day of the head-bath, everything
looked spick-and-span, but the next day, my whole head was filled with scales of dead skin. Soon, my favourite
pastime became, taking a newspaper and combing my dandruff onto it and
wondering in bewilderment at the amount of skin I had shed. Applying coconut oil
made the flakes gooey, like oversoaked breakfast cereal. Skipping it made it
look fresh, ready to be thrown it into a bowl.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did I know, that, the shampoo was making the problem worse, by taking away
the natural oil layer secreted by the skin. The skin panics on detecting this loss and secretes more
of its oil, which becomes a bumper food supply for the fungus on our skin, which
grow exponentially, triggering the skin cells to molt
in profusion. Ignorant of this complexity,
I increased the frequency of shampoo use and ended up with just a bigger
dandruff mound on the newspaper.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=EmiqG_XdePY&quot;&gt;a video by &lt;em&gt;Dave
Hakkens&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which introduced me to
the &lt;em&gt;No Poo&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; movement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stopped using shampoo, or for that matter even our traditional alternatives
like &lt;em&gt;shikakai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Instead I started washing my hair daily with just plain water and
also skipped applying coconut oil, in an attempt to deprive the fungus of fatty oils. After a few months things looked better. The
absence of, the day-after-the-head-bath flare-up, itself, was a big relief. I have continued this with
good success for maybe 10 years now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the period when I slowly moved away from hot water to unheated water
for bathing. This also likely helped reduce the stress on the skin as hot water
can remove natural skin oils more, than cold water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold water for bathing was something that I dreaded from my childhood. There was
this children&#x27;s magazine called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wisdom.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wisdom&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; where I had read
that bathing in cold water is the best for the human body. In spite of this, I
could never make this a habit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from my home to my college in Pondicherry was a 3 hour journey that I
used to make almost every week and invariably it was a Monday morning. I had to
bath at around 4:30 AM, and hot water was what I used. Even then, by the time I
reached college, I had sweated so much during the bus journey, that I felt 
uncomfortable sitting in the class, I even started walking all the way to the
hostel to take a cold shower and walked back to the college, sometimes being
late or skipping the first hour. During this time I
tried experimenting with taking bath in cold water instead of hot water,
before I started from home on the bus journey. Remarkably I sweated much less
and felt more fresh when I reached college.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with this, first-hand proof, it was more than 10 years later, that cold
showers became a habit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I started skipping during this time, was, using bathing soap. I know, this
might be shocking and you might feel uneasy coming close to me, after knowing
this fact, but no one has complained to me, yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the &lt;em&gt;No Poo&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; process, I do not use any traditional replacements like
moong dal powder or the other umpteen things which people have suggested.
Initially I just used &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Luffa&quot;&gt;dried ridge gourd
sponge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to scrub my skin, but after a few months I started using it less
frequently. Now, I use the soap or the scrub very rarely, only in case I want to remove things like
oil, glue, paint or cement that are stuck to my skin. Otherwise, I just make good use of my hand
fingers and nails and in the process realizing how inflexible my hands were in
reaching my back. I also made good use of the towel I used to dry myself and
felt that the soap is better used on it than my body.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the daily cold water head-bath regimen running successfully, I did notice
that there was still some amount of dandruff and I realized, the daily head bath
may not be necessary. So now, I have switched to just a weekly head bath or sooner if I felt they were dirty. In
addition, I apply a bit of coconut oil on the hair after the head bath, as it
reduces the oil secreted by my scalp even more and keeps the fungus under
control. Now everything seems to be in a steady state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Wow, so, are the people who invented shampoo and soaps, fools?&amp;quot; I hear people ask.
If they have no use, how did they
get so popular? I suppose, they served a very narrow purpose when they were
invented. These were likely game changing and so they became popular, but soon they were being used even when they
were not necessary. Shampoo and soap are still the most advertised products on
television, serving very much as a proof that, only unnecessary products are
advertised. Antibiotics, paracetamol, sugar, fertilizers, the over-used-products list may just be growing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still fancy myself thinking, the marketing team of Procter and Gamble got word
of my findings and has spent crores of rupees &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=TMGQXeN6iqg&quot;&gt;on this
ad&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to shame me back into using their
product. &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Dandruff thirumba varave varathu&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, they plead, with the sincerity of a
car salesman.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Darebee healthy</title>
		<published>2024-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/darebee-healthy/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/darebee-healthy/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After an acute spike in my blood sugar in November 2020, I embarked on a strict
process involving keto diet, intermittent fasting and strength training
exercises. More than 5 years before that, I was diagnosed with fatty liver which
I largely ignored and was visibly overweight, reaching 90 kgs. After the
intervention, I probably lost around 20 kg of weight and 4 inches in waist size
over a period of around a year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise was indispensible part of this process. Cost many times does indicate
quality, but when it comes to knowledge and learning, it is always a contra
indicator. What is costly is priced for the easy path shown to acheive a metric, which by requirement needs to be easily measured. But these metrics are only a proxy for the outcome that you desire, which only time can reveal. I was always wary of buying education. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I viewed my exercise journey as an education process and decided to seek out
high quality sources which aren&#x27;t manufactured specifically to sell to me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;@RowanRow&quot;&gt;Rowen Row&#x27;s channel on Youtube&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with mostly following this no equipment exercise routine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;9tT8afUt7kM?si=YPndX_pS7_rHW4ZV&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months I wanted a bit more of variety and started on a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;playlist?list=PLLXmeIOBkPXRV32fch2mbJgHK8k0xu31n&quot;&gt;28 day
fitness program based on videos by a person called Ashley
Conrad&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
I still remember not being able to stand on one leg without holding on to a support when doing the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=YdB1HMCldJY&amp;amp;list=PLLXmeIOBkPXRV32fch2mbJgHK8k0xu31n&amp;amp;index=4&amp;amp;t=324s&quot;&gt;standing quadricep
stretch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
It is likely an early indicator of the neural damage which can lead to
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Parkinson%27s_disease&quot;&gt;Parkinson&#x27; disease&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. After more than 3 years of practise, I have gained my
balance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the real world uses of strength is in fights and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Mixed_martial_arts&quot;&gt;Mixed Martial
Arts&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or MMA piqued my
interest. I enjoyed watching the fights and read through &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;6966926-the-ultimate-mixed-martial-arts-training-guide&quot;&gt;The Ultimate Mixed
Martial Arts Training
Guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by Dann Plyler. This talked more about the philosophy and techniques used. The book,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;1735237.Training_for_Warriors&quot;&gt;Trainig for
Warriors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by
Martin Rooney had a bit more on exercise routines and I diligently practised them
for a few months.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any good habit, it is easy break a streak and getting back on track is
difficult. I often lose interest and many times my thrifty thought of &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;exercise
is a waste of time and resources and instead I should rely more on manual work&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;,
takes over. Also now that I am in a far better shape, I am no longer motivated
enough to do the strenuous 1 hour sessions I used to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;darebee.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DAREBEE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; website helps a lot. I found
this a year back and it was my next stop after the MMA encounter. DAREBEE has bite
sized pages that focus on a specific theme and has  multiple difficulty levels.
These can also be conveniently downloaded as a PDF to help refer during
exercises, wherever you are. Now that I am familiar with the basic movements and
their functions, I no longer need complete videos. The wide
variety of the exercise collection and the interesting gamification in some of
them all help sustain the streaks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also whenever I am in this mixed mood of not wanting to exercise but also
feeling awful because I am not, I push myself to do 10 squats
and 10 pushups before my morning bath. This often helps me get back on
my streak.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word of  caution: most body weight exercises have very little risk of injury
compared to external weights. But always listen to your body and not over exert.
Do sufficient warmup before your exercise and have sufficient breaks and rest
days, during and after
the exercise. You will hear this a lot from everyone, but it cannot be over
emphasized.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Killers of the flower moon and diabetes</title>
		<published>2024-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/killers-of-the-flower-moon-and-diabetes/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/killers-of-the-flower-moon-and-diabetes/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Killers_of_the_Flower_Moon_(film)&quot;&gt;Killers of the flower
moon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a long
slow movie about the predicament of the people of the Osage tribe after oil was
found on their land. This is based on real life incidents which took place in
Oklahama in the USA in the 1920s which was also part of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Killers_of_the_Flower_Moon_(book)&quot;&gt;Killers of the
Flower Moon: The Osage Murders and the Birth of the
FBI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of threads in the film, but the main focus is on the humans
succumbing to greed. The thread that most struck me was something that many
people were surprised when I first mentioned it to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Osage people, as with all socities that did not use fossil fuels, had to
depend on human and animal labour for their survival. Both agriculture and hunting
provided an active lifestyle and kept them healthy. When oil was found on their
land, they were given royalties which they spent on cars, servants and other
riches which changed their lifestyle suddenly. Soon there was an epidemic of
diabetes which was followed by hordes of doctors helping &#x27;cure&#x27; it by trying out
the newly discovered insulin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds similar to our generation and our parents&#x27;?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why was there a stark effect on the Osage people when the white men also had
changes to their lifestyle due to oil and coal? I can only guess: the shift in
lifestyle happened more suddenly for these people and for centuries they
had to do more physical activity than the Europeans.
Coupled with the &#x27;free money&#x27; and the general loss of agency leading to addiction —
not just to liquor and other substances, but just simply the new food.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other people have also noticed this thread and have written about it. For example,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;medicine.yale.edu&#x2F;news-article&#x2F;what-the-killers-of-the-flower-moon-movie-teaches-us-about-historical-trauma-and-indigenous-health&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this article on the Yale: School of
medicine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;slate.com&#x2F;culture&#x2F;2023&#x2F;10&#x2F;killers-of-the-flower-moon-movie-mollie-burkhart-diabetes-indigenous-native-osage-history.html&quot;&gt;this one on the Slate&#x27;s
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
But I would surely like more publicity on the diabetes thread in this movie.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
