<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>My Experiments</title>
	<subtitle>My Blog and Projects</subtitle>
	<link href="https://arunkd13.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://arunkd13.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>K. P. Park</title>
		<published>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/kp-park/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/kp-park/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I participated in one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Tamil_Nadu_Urban_Habitat_Development_Board&quot;&gt;TNUHDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; audits that Arappor Iyakkam does periodically. This was at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;52oTqCWz686iGv8J7&quot;&gt;K. P. Park&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on De Mellows Road in Pulianthope that is also famous for the abysmal plastering and finishing work for which Arappor Iyakkam had previously raised a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=jZjMUoie_ns&quot;&gt;complaint with DVAC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the volunteers had gathered at the meeting point, and we could see the towering buildings painted in bright inviting colors, looking better than I had imagined. We entered the site and went into the nearest block. The more experienced volunteers immediately chose to survey the lifts, since it had become a concern after a person lost his life inside it due to an accident around a year back.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We approached the lift operator who was quite friendly and he told that only one of the lifts was working. The other one had not been funcitoning for the past 3 months. A quick enquiry with other residents waiting for the lift and we got numbers like 1.5 years. The lifts in the next block we visited was in a worse situation. The operator said only one of the two lifts functioned. But when we tried to press the button to summon the lift, he said, &amp;quot;Sir, wait, I will go to the second floor and bring it down. The button doesn&#x27;t work&amp;quot;. Yes, he was telling the truth. The lift works. Only the button doesn&#x27;t work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These towers had something like 10 to 12 floors and lifts were absolutely essential. Only one of the towers we visited had a working generator backup. The other one was supposedly under repair after rats chewed away the wires. This was on a Sunday evening and I can only imagine the chaos during rush hours on a working day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we came down the stairs from the 10th floor, we saw the other stark problem of K. P. Park. Garbage was strewn all over the stair case. We continued descending, placing each step with caution. Suddenly we stepped on a landing that was unusually clean. Someone wise, had pasted a wall paper with Mother Mary holding Baby Jesus in her hands. A makeshift shrine on the vertical roadways of K. P. Park.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming down we couldn&#x27;t stop noticing garbage that followed us everywhere we looked. The OTS areas were the most affected with more than a dozen rats making a happy meal out of it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to the residents, we came to know that the conservancy workers clean it every day, but it gets filled very soon by residents in the top floors dropping their daily waste directly out of their windows. There have also been &lt;em&gt;accidents&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; where someone had inadvertently stepped under such a falling bag. The conservancy workers have all been given helmets to safe guard their heads as they go about cleaning the area.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had learnt in the audit pre-brief that many of the TNUHDB tenements had Resident Welfare Associations (RWAs) that ran the maintenance and were also responsible for spending the fund allocated by the Government. At K. P. Park, none of the blocks had one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also seemed to be vertical segregation happening with the less previlieged people relocated recently from nearby areas like Egmore allocated residences on the top floors. While the people who had been living in the previous settlement that had been demolished to build this highrise, put up in the lower floors. One of the residents put the blame for the garbage squarely on &amp;quot;...those uncivilized people living on the top floors. What can the government do?&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if mixing less privileged people across all floors would help the situation. But the same forces that end up pushing people dispersed througout the city into this single town within a city, are also likely oprating within this town.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if mixing the less previliged people across all the floors would help the situation. But the same forces that end up pushing people dispersed throughout the city into this single town within a city, are also likely operating within this town.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing people for the better is always a difficult task. More than anti-corruption activists, what this settlement needs are community organizers. Will we be able to fill these shoes?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>NCERT Exemplar</title>
		<published>2025-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/ncert-exemplar/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/ncert-exemplar/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NCERT publishes a series of additional material to their text books called,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ncert.nic.in&#x2F;exemplar-problems.php?ln=en&quot;&gt;Exemplar Problems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. They
provide this for Maths and Science subjects from Class VI to XII. This is
really valuable for preparing for the exams and are used by both kids and
teachers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the website provides only individual PDF files for each chapter.
Also, the PDF file is a pre-production version with paper size markings which
increases the page size.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these make it difficult to read on a small ereader and the kids get
another reason to use the computer and eventually get distracted by the umpteen
games and Youtube videos that can also be accessed from there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed a way to combine the individual PDFs into a single file and also crop
the pages. There are a number of ways of doing this, but after a few trial and
errors, I settled on the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pdfarranger&#x2F;pdfarranger&quot;&gt;PDF
Arranger&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; tool. I also did a print
to PDF as a final step on my Gnome desktop and selected the option to &#x27;fit to
page&#x27;, so that, all the pages have the standard A4 size, instead of the
cropped sizes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the final PDF now, which I loaded onto my Kindle. The text was readable,
but it was still a subpar experience. My &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Amazon_Kindle&quot;&gt;7th Gen
Kindle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
bought in 2015 was showing its age.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I ended up creating A5 size books by
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Imposition&quot;&gt;imposing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; two of the original pages
on an A4 paper using the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bookbinder.app&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Book Binder&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; tool. I used
the chain stitch that is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=0gDHKZcdgDg&quot;&gt;explained in this
video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some additional help from a few scraps of card board, an old jeans, a chart paper and
Fevicol, I now had a decent book whose binding was way better than commercially
produced books, because the book can be laid flat due to using small bundles of
pages that are stitched together called Signature. The papers also stay put for
a long time, unlike the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Bookbinding#Thermally_activated_binding&quot;&gt;Perfect
bound&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
cheap paper backs, whose bindings fail after a few years and pages fall off
randomly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See it here in all its glory.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafkreifa2xh4olozmai6y3s2bmhe5oeuwrpiwwmlsnv767pyvgxgqx52ny&quot; alt=&quot;The bound book&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book with pages opened flat.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafkreiav3p4oqqb64emcha7hlrkybn2tk6bfvywq5req3ip3rmafhfhvxa&quot; alt=&quot;Opened flat&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had previously made similar hand bound books for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;standardebooks.org&#x2F;ebooks&#x2F;epictetus&#x2F;discourses&#x2F;george-long&quot;&gt;Discourses by
Epictetus&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and a fiction written by my friend called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sophia-publishing.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;The Archer&#x27;s
Revenge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I was happy that I could use
this new found hobby of mine in a more conventional way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the PDF versions of the book in case you woudl find it useful:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeihyg3gedp6b3xowurf7li3qww6duemjhx3d4w2tybnppwq5f3qi6y&quot;&gt;10th-maths-exemplar.pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeibp4l3q3ryzb6f5prprcpzmvlkmxw5vgc3bplsmbhfjs2l22mdghi&quot;&gt;10th-science-exemplar.pdf&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Breaking into a car and making duplicate keys</title>
		<published>2025-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/breaking-into-a-car-and-duplicate-keys/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/breaking-into-a-car-and-duplicate-keys/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When we bought our car, a Hyundai i10, in 2008, we received two keys and I was a
happy driver for 16 years. If we mistakenly left the keys inside and got
ourselves locked out of the car, the spare key saved the day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, our car met with an accident and was towed away to the police
station. Fortunately no one was hurt. We all learn from our mistakes, and we
become a slightly better driver after an accident. But this one also taught me
lessons of a different kind.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was on the day of a relative&#x27;s engagement. The car that hit ours was a
Bolero pickup truck and didn&#x27;t show any signs of impact other than a small dent
on its left bumper. But the Hyundai i10&#x27;s front right side fender, wheel and
axle where totalled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The police didn&#x27;t agree to let us tow the car to our place and wanted both
parties to come to the station with the vehicle. In retrospect, I should have
gone to the station along with the car and dealt with the matter the same day.
But I did not know better at that time and succumbed to the pressure to attend
the function. The situation was further muddied by assurances from the Panchayat
president of the nearby village, that I can deal with it the next day and didn&#x27;t have
to worry. He was also a relative.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I soon realized that this was one of the stupidest thing to do. Showing the
least care for your property and trusting the police to protect it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We sought the help of a lawyer, who negotiated with the police. It took a few
days for the police to confirm that the other party would not proceed with filing a
case and to agree to return the confiscated property.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I eagerly went to the Police station along with the lawyer the same evening. I
was asked to write a letter with the details of the incident which included the
statement that the police have duly returned the confiscated vehicle, and I
agreed to report back with the car if there was any further inquiry or action
needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these were the regular procedure and the lawyer handling it made it less
stressful for me. But unfortunately, after giving the letter, they searched for
the key, and it was nowhere to be found. We rummaged through two boxes full of
keys from vehicles with a similar plight. The police said that the person who
was on duty might have misplaced it, and he would be on duty only the next day.
I would have to use the duplicate key until then.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duplicate key was in Chennai and the car was in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;4X8JV1xESQeMGUFAA&quot;&gt;Mailam police
station&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a distance of 135 km. We
had already given the letter to the police before we were informed of the
missing key.  Refusing to pick up the car now and asking for the letter to be
returned would sour the matters, and cause more work for me. The lawyer too was
in no mood to confront the police. Now that I remember the small talk he had
with the constables on first name basis, I realized he would be even less
interested than me in creating a ruckus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We weighed our options for opening the door. The lawyer called one of his
juniors, who conveniently also ran an automotive scrapyard. After a bit of small
talk with him, I made him realize that I was in no mood to scrap the car. He
asked for a metal scale from the police station, tore of the weather stripping,
inserted it between the door and the window glass and started playing around
with it trying to open the lock.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the guy who we had called to tow the car to a local garage, suggested
that he could either call up someone to pick the lock or just break the quarter
pane glass and open the car. As I was slowly weighing my options, the lawyer
made a more quick decision and asked the driver to call up the lock pickers. It
was already getting dark now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three guys arrived at the scene on a Honda Activa and started randomly
disconnecting wires on the front and around the headlights.  Another guy started
playing around with the scale inserted in the window, replacing the junior
advocate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt like my car was being violated by five men and that blew my fuse off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Stop!&amp;quot; I shouted. &amp;quot;Why are you disconnecting the wires, without asking me?
Don&#x27;t you realize that there is no electronic theft device installed?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was angry at the thought that they might break other things while trying to
open the lock. I would be the one who would have to live with the consequences.
There was no way these people would prioritize my interests. They were here for
the easy money, that came from exploiting my helplessness. They didn&#x27;t care
about reducing further loss to my property, but only about extracting the
maximum amount of money from me. It wasn&#x27;t without reason that three people had
come to pick a single lock which did not require man power but skill, patience
and focus. The closest situation to this I had faced was when my father had
developed a brain tumour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I know you are a bunch of amateurs. Get lost&amp;quot;, I shouted again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since they had just begun to work, it was easier for me to kick them out with a
bit more of posturing. Fortunately, they left without extracting any money from me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked the towing service driver to break the quarter pane. I had already
checked the price, and it was just around Rs. 600, including shipping.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The driver took a lever from his boot, gave quick wack on the glass with it, and
soon we were on our way to the garage, with the car in tow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward a few years, and I was once again in the same situation, this time
purely my doing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I was working on the front right door of our car after removing the door
trim. I was trying to replace the side view mirror which was knocked off its
fixture. I couldn&#x27;t remember how it happened. My best guess was the pesky
neighbourhood kids, who I last saw playing ice-boy—now Americanized to
hide-and-seek—running up and down the stairs beside which the car was parked.
Now don&#x27;t mistake me for an old curmudgeon&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a bit of guidance from a few YouTube videos, I soon completed the task.
Feeling proud, I hurried to take a break.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I returned a few minutes later to clear up the tools, I couldn&#x27;t open the
door. I had forgotten to check the lock position before slamming the door shut,
and the key was still in the ignition switch. What a stupid mistake I had done.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the occasions when you really wish you had a time machine so that you
can go back and kick your past self on their butt right when they are about to
do that one action which changes their lives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stood there frozen, playing the events that happened in the last few minutes
over and over in my mind. No one turned up with a time machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I swallowed my pride and went through my options. I searched
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;boodmo.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;boodmo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the price was around Rs. 450. There was
another item already in the cart and showed a shipping charge of Rs. 150. I
concluded that the price was around the same that I had paid a year before and
decided to break into my car, once again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tested a few items like a box spanner and screwdriver, hitting the quarter
pane with them. The glass was too strong, and all of them bounced back with just
a few scratches left on the glass. I realized I needed something more hefty and
with a sharp point. Immediately I remembered something that would do the work. I
ran into the house, got hold of a bill hook and tapped the pointed end on the
glass, imagining all the Tamil movies I had watched. The pane shattered into a
thousand little diamonds held together by cheap cellophane.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While carefully removing the broken bits of glass from the seat and floor, I
silently vowed, to get the spare key made first before replacing the broken
glass.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with some quick research on the Internet and there were machines made
by the ever innovative tool vendors from Coimbatore which &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=8-qh_XQPhfg&quot;&gt;duplicated a key onto
a blank by using a cutting disk that moved by tracing the original
key&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. There were also blank keys
being sold for the i10 online that cost Rs. 300.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wished I could buy the cutting machine and make my own duplicate key, but at
my scale even a file set wouldn&#x27;t be worth the returns on my money.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a locksmith required years of practice. You could see them on the
roadsides setting shop with just a small vice, hacksaw and a file set. They had
immense skill and would whip out a duplicate key from the hundreds of blanks on
display, before you knew it. The quality of the fitting jobs I had done in the
mechanical workshop at college were still fresh in my mind. I started to look
for a locksmith.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.google.com&#x2F;maps&#x2F;place&#x2F;13%C2%B005&amp;#x27;15.8%22N+80%C2%B011&amp;#x27;27.5%22E&#x2F;@13.0877875,80.1908324,333m&#x2F;&quot;&gt;round building
shops&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
a landmark around Mogappair, and a place filled with all manners of low
investment trades. After a few enquiries, I located a locksmith&#x27;s shop, but they
all seemed to have been put out of work by the machine. They still had their
shops, but now used them as price gouging fronts. They would tell that it would
take two days for the key to be made and take the key to another vendor who
owned the duplicating machine. It had become a low turnover, high margin
business.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enquired with the person sitting lazily on a stool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;OK, here talk to the owner&amp;quot;, he said. I took the phone and told my situation
and asked how much a duplicate key would cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I can quote only after seeing the car, Sir&amp;quot;, the locksmith replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I told him the make, model and year and also said there were no electronic security
system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It would cost Rs. 1800&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What? Why do you need so much for a simple key?&amp;quot; I asked expressing my shock.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, there is a chip inside the key&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Really? This is what people told when the Rs. 2000 note was released&amp;quot;, I chuckled.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The locksmith was not pleased with my sense of humour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;OK, I will call you once I get hold of the key. What is your name?&amp;quot; I asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Daniel&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked into the Tirumangalam Metro station I took a photo of the key and
sent it to Daniel through WhatsApp. I boarded the next train to central on my
way to GP Road.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GP Road is right behind the famous LIC building and was the Mecca of original
auto parts in Chennai. I was looking at all the sign boards placed in the shops,
as I walked past, for any indication of key duplication services. Finally, I
spotted a photo of a car key on a shop called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;net8JSx45uy2g2oh9&quot;&gt;Nachiappa
Stickers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name sounded familiar and looked like a reputed shop. I went inside and
showed the key to the attendant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There might be a chip embedded in the plastic moulding, Sir. In that case, the
duplicate can be used only to open the door and will not start the engine. If
you also want to drive the car, you need to contact the dealer to get the key&amp;quot;,
he said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;That is OK, how much does the duplicate cost?&amp;quot; I asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Rs. 150&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounded a better deal. &amp;quot;Go ahead and make me one&amp;quot;, I said handing over the
key.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In just under a minute, he came back with a new key with neatly cut grooves
matching the original.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If it does not open, should I do any sanding or filing to fit it?&amp;quot; I asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;No Sir, it will fit perfectly&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then stopped at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;8CaK88WvvdiqYCA36&quot;&gt;Jehangir&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; where I
had bought the quarter pane glass earlier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It would cost Rs. 900&amp;quot;, the attendant replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was way more than what I had budgeted after checking the price on boodmo.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Is there any other cheaper option?&amp;quot; I enquired.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Try Pudupet&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pudupet is the other automotive Mecca, situated on the opposite side of the
Cooum river, from GP Road. It is famous for refurbished parts from old and more
famously stolen vehicles. I had driven through the place a few times but never
had a good look at the shops. I decided to pay my visits to this place too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked across the bridge, I saw the usual sewage flowing in the Cooum
river.  The stench was unbearable. The pilgrim&#x27;s road is never comfortable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pudupet had a bit of an old world charm to it. After walking past some shops
there was this large shady tree. The kind under which a village headman would
sit to decide a local dispute. A shed with its doors locked stood under it now.
The name board said, &amp;quot;Police at door step&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I walked past, I couldn&#x27;t see any shops specializing in glass. It was mostly
reworked engines, exhausts, suspensions and lots of cheap new accessories. I
didn&#x27;t want to waste time enquiring anywhere as I had already made up my mind
that it would be too much of a gamble buying from here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked a bit more and ended up at the Egmore railway station and boarded the
metro back to Tirumangalam.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I got out of the metro, I received a voice message with a quote from Daniel.
&amp;quot;There is no chip in this key Sir. It will cost Rs. 550&amp;quot;, he said.  I posted
a &#x27;Thank You&#x27; emoji, feeling happy on the savings I made.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back home, I logged into boodmo to order the glass, but it showed a shipping cost
of Rs. 500 which brought the cost to Rs. 950. I cursed myself for assuming the
shipping cost and the government for the inflation and started looking for any
vendor closer to home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;teqzKfjepef7NBeJ7&quot;&gt;Calcutta Glass in Arumbakkam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; seemed
to be the nearest store. I called the shop, and they quoted Rs. 950. This was
still a better option than boodmo as I didn&#x27;t have to wait for 10 days, or so I
thought. Instead, I ended up being cheated by this guy who sold me a piece with
a number of scratches. I realize now that I should have followed him when he
took the piece inside for packing. A common ruse in the big bad world outside of
Amazon. Running to the shop once again for replacement that may or may not come,
wasn&#x27;t worth the time and money. I realize now why people vacillate towards
Amazon even when it pulls up a few dirty tricks on its own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I am all set to attempt replacing the glass, without fear of locking myself
out. No one would even guess that the glass was replaced as it looks as old as
the car with scratches that mimics age. More importantly I was thankful that I
did not have an engine immobilizer that requires the chip in the key to be
reprogrammed, nor a car costly enough to require an engine immobilizer.
Innovation is about selling a problem as a solution, so that you can keep
innovating.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Precalculus by Stitz-Zeager</title>
		<published>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/precalculus-stitz-zeager/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/precalculus-stitz-zeager/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was searching for a challenging maths book that would help my kids get
ready for learning Calculus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was looking for something which was a classic and which could be easily loaded
onto a small 6&amp;quot; Kindle e-reader so that I didn&#x27;t have to print it out.  That is
when I came across this excellent book called
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;stitz-zeager.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Precalculus&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; written by Carl Stitz and Jeff Zeager,
and released under Creative Commons Licence along with the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;stitz-zeager.com&#x2F;Precalc4Source.zip&quot;&gt;LaTeX source
code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was excited and quickly downloaded it, updated the paper size to A6 and
rebuilt the PDF. But it looks like the LaTeX maths environment does not reflow
the equations and requires manual splitting to fit into the page width. Also,
the tables and the exercise sections used multiple columns, assuming a larger
paper width and got cropped when the paper size was reduced.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this is open source, I decided to start a new personal project to reformat
this book. If you are interested, do join me in this effort. Code available on
GitHub: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;precalculus&quot;&gt;arunkd13&#x2F;precalculus&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Before you ask, I searched for anyone else who had already started on this
work, but couldn&#x27;t find anyone. I have also emailed Carl and waiting for a reply.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Seeking action against TANGEDCO and the Adani Group</title>
		<published>2024-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/tangedco-adani-scam/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/tangedco-adani-scam/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Late evening of January 3, 2025, a bit more than 24 hours from the
planned time of protest, Arappor Iyakkam was informed by the Commissioner of
Police, that their request for permission to protest was denied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the protest, we had to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=pTiIMpn80Xo&quot;&gt;protest against the rejection of permission
to protest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; within the confines of
the Arappor Iyakkam office.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Arappor Iyakkam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has called for a protest against the
Central and Tamil Nadu State Governments on January 5, 2025 at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;iBBSm2h2WBVP6gUH9&quot;&gt;Valluvar Kottam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, seeking
action against
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Tamil_Nadu_Generation_and_Distribution_Corporation&quot;&gt;TANGEDCO&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and the Adani Group on the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.occrp.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;investigation&#x2F;new-evidence-bolsters-allegations-adani-group-overcharged-for-coal&quot;&gt;substandard coal purchase
scam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pbs.twimg.com&#x2F;media&#x2F;GfAULtLaUAA8q2k?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=small&quot; alt=&quot;India is not for sale&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no dearth of allegations of corruption, bribes, scams and fraud against
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Adani_Group&quot;&gt;Adani Group&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;—more than half
their Wikipedia page is dedicated to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, many people say, this is all an international conspiracy to limit the
growth rate of India&#x27;s GDP and prevent it from becoming a “superpower”. But,
they give the same answer even when we ask why the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.google.com&#x2F;finance&#x2F;quote&#x2F;USD-INR?hl=en&amp;amp;window=MAX&quot;&gt;value of the
INR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has fallen
by more than 30 %, with respect to the USD, from the day Prime Minister
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Narendra_Modi&quot;&gt;Narendra Modi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; took office in
2014.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Indian_National_Developmental_Inclusive_Alliance&quot;&gt;INDIA
coalition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
of which the DMK is a part of, is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;economictimes.indiatimes.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;politics-and-nation&#x2F;india-bloc-mps-hold-protest-in-parliament-complex-over-adani-issue-demand-jpc-probe&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;115961485.cms&quot;&gt;demanding a JPC
probe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on the allegations against the Adani Group in the wake of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Indictment_against_Gautam_Adani_et_al.&quot;&gt;indictment
against Gautam Adani et
al.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in a
US District Court.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Chief Minister &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;M._K._Stalin&quot;&gt;M. K. Stalin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
who is part of this coalition had also been a vehement opposer of the “corrupt
Adani Group”, but it was before he was elected as CM in 2021. He hasn&#x27;t shown
the same fervour, now that he has the power to prosecute them. Would this
be the same that the Congress and Rahul Gandhi would do if elected to power?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This double faced politics and people&#x27;s helplessness towards it, is very
dangerous. Crony capitalism at a different time, helped the East India Company
take over India. If we intend to retain our hard-earned freedom, we need to be
vigilant against it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus on the TANGEDCO-Adani Coal Scam and the Chief
Minister M. K. Stalin is just a tool in the fight against this bigger problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 9, 2018:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The leader of the opposition Mr. M. K. Stalin, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;stalin-demands-cbi-probe-into-coal-import&#x2F;article22696633.ece&quot;&gt;demanded a CBI
probe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on the alleged import of substandard coal by TANGEDCO, benefiting the Adani
Group. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Edappadi_K._Palaniswami&quot;&gt;Edapadi K.
Palaniswami&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of the AIADMK
was the Chief Minister at that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 6, 2018:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Arappor Iyakkam &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeifgcqe4olo4k5shdgt4bvw27abirnzhwf7w7abxqrzmejcu4u6rra&quot;&gt;submitted a
complaint&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
with the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.dvac.tn.gov.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Department of Vigilance and
Anti-Corruption&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on this import of substandard coal
and corresponding loss to the exchequer of around ₹6066 crores.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 4, 2019:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Arappor Iyakkam submitted &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeibwjgqfjhhbujvleoasstckkyaxmfzbuxj5zxzbtrbzhwzntlj6ni&quot;&gt;additional
evidence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to the DVAC on the lower pricing of the coal purchased by TNPL compared to
TANGEDCO for the same quality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 2021:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Stalin became the Chief Minister. The once vehement opposer of corruption in TANGEDCO, let the complaints languish with the DVAC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 31, 2023:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, Arappor Iyakkam reminded him by sending a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeihj2qqqhejgp2cefetma67otfmou35sq76ffgycvy5kq7qdqpspkq&quot;&gt;letter &lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
demanding that the DVAC immediately start investigating the complaint and register an FIR against TANGEDCO officials
and the Adani Group.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2, 2024:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; It was widely reported that the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;tamil-nadu-probe-launched-into-coal-import-scam-involving-adani-group&#x2F;article68359304.ece&quot;&gt;DVAC has got the nod from the
State
Government&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and had registered a preliminary enquiry on the allegations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In just a few days on July 9, 2024:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Gautam Adani flew down to Chennai on a chartered plane and according to
a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&#x2F;city&#x2F;chennai&#x2F;adani-groups-interest-in-parandur-airport-and-kattupalli-port-creates-buzz-in-chennai&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;111644935.cms&quot;&gt;report in The Times of India&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, visited Chittaranjan Salai—the residence of CM
Stalin—and then left for a dinner meeting on the ECR, before returning home the same
night.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RTI requests by Arappor Iyakkam to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dipr.tn.gov.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DIPR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, gave a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pbs.twimg.com&#x2F;media&#x2F;GfDsMw3WwAATwKU?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=large&quot;&gt;response that they did not have any information on Adani&#x27;s
visit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
although the Tamil Nadu Police was involved in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=7Z6FyvphMGs&quot;&gt;security arrangements as
seen in this video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other political parties like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;cms-son-in-law-sabareesan-met-adani-bjp-state-president-annamalai&#x2F;article68973903.ece&quot;&gt;BJP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&#x2F;city&#x2F;chennai&#x2F;ramadoss-demands-stalins-explanation-on-tangedcos-ties-with-adani&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;115534839.cms&quot;&gt;PMK&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.business-standard.com&#x2F;politics&#x2F;aiadmk-slams-tamil-nadu-cm-stalin-says-he-is-a-pathological-liar-124121100061_1.html&quot;&gt;AIADMK&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
have caught on to this scandal and have used it to corner the DMK, while they
themselves, do not support any investigations on the Adani Group at the centre.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire Government and Political System seem to benefit from the Adani Group
and are afraid to act against them. In all these, the common man stands to lose
the most.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel pained by what we see and want to do something to change
the situation, but do not know what to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Democracy, political parties are still at the mercy of elections, votes and
ultimately the people (though there are attempts to weaken this power through
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;One_Nation,_One_Election&quot;&gt;One Nation, One
Election&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; proposal).
They still fear them more than any Adani, but we fail to raise our voice loud
enough to reach their ears. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;nyaaya.org&#x2F;resource&#x2F;guide-to-lawful-protesting&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Peaceful
protests&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
demonstrations are the loudest alarm bells, while views, likes and comments on
social media are sweet lullabies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope, I have convinced you to stand with Arappor Iyakkam on January 5, at
Valluvar Kottam and make our voices heard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSVP: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;RegisterForAdaniProtestEvent&quot;&gt;Register For Adani Protest Event&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Arappor Iyakkam</title>
		<published>2024-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/arappor-iyakkam/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/arappor-iyakkam/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently started volunteering with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Arappor Iyakkam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
which is a civil society organization that fights for an accountable government.
I had been following their work for the past 6 to 7 years, and now that I have
some time to spare, I decided to spend at least one day a week volunteering with
them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first activity that I participated was the audit of the tenders that were
given out by the Greater Chennai Corporation for restoring water bodies. These
were for works like deepening the lake or pond and constructing bunds and
pathways around them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well known that, the tenders given to contractors for public works are a
major source of corruption, and it was heartening to see common citizens banding
together to make sure our tax money is not wasted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked two water bodies viz. Karuppan Kulam and Vairavan Pond, both near
Ambattur. As instructed by the coordinator I visited both the water bodies, took
extensive photographs of the restoration work that was underway and also talked
to a few residents to gather information on when the work carried out and
submitted them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volunteering with them has shown a glimpse of the extensive field work they do
and the effort involved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One gripe was that I did not receive enough visibility of the overall progress
of the project. There was only one full time employee who coordinated all the
volunteers through WhatsApp. He was clearly overburdened, and I could not expect
him to worry about volunteer engagement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hoping to see more information on this campaign in the coming months and
see how effective it is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Vacant Land Tax</title>
		<published>2024-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/vacant-land-tax/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/vacant-land-tax/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the year 2017, the Chennai Corporation (later called Greater Chennai
Corporation or GCC), started imposing a tax on vacant land within its
boundaries. This was to discourage land hoarders—and more importantly, to
increase their revenue.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple way to pass on generational wealth that was accessible to the common
man, became less economical. It might be justified if the government did a
better job of enforcing land grabbing laws in the city, but it is not the case.
Police for their part, in cahoots with the politicians impose their own tax.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vacant land tax seems to have been initiated by other urban bodies in Tamil
Nadu, and the other states too, around the same time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had inherited one such parcel of land in 2008 and had to pay my dues, before I
could exercise my rights to develop it. But as usual, this straight forward
task was made needlessly tedious, by our government officers and politicians,
and an opportunity for them to profit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chennai Corporation&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;gcc&#x2F;department&#x2F;revenue&#x2F;#revenue&quot;&gt;Revenue Department has very detailed information on
their website explaining all their procedures&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and the formula for calculating the vacant land tax. Along with the &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;departments&#x2F;revenue&#x2F;StreetRates&#x2F;Z-13%20STREETRATE.pdf&quot;&gt;Basic
Street Rate (BSR), for zone
13&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
I was able to get an idea of the tax I would have to pay.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found a document explaining the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;gcc&#x2F;SOP&#x2F;REVENUE_SOP.pdf&quot;&gt;SOP for all revenue department
procedures&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
another document giving the SOP specifically for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tnswp.com&#x2F;DIGIGOV&#x2F;StaticAttachment?AttachmentFileName=&#x2F;procedure&#x2F;pre_op&#x2F;PO_34.pdf&quot;&gt;new assessment of property
tax&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
The process for vacant land tax assessment was essentially the same as any
regular property tax assessment that you make for a built house or any other
structure.  The entire process had an SLA of 30 days. There was also &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;erp.chennaicorporation.gov.in&#x2F;e-portal&#x2F;login.do&quot;&gt;a website
where an online application can be made for the
assessment&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, in
addition to other services.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good, and I was happy with our Digital India!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I completed the form and tried to submit the application, and I got a 502
error—looks like our officials had managed to sabotage the online process. What
is advantageous for the citizen, is likely, not so for them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a paper form for new tax assessment that came up in search results,
but it had umpteen columns and details, that I decided to go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;mbHyH4KNGTREYzTt5&quot;&gt;zonal
office in Adyar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to enquire. I have
too many scars from my engineering college days, when highly educated lab staff
would throw my meticulously crafted record out, for not having used the same format
as my seniors. Yes, they too had a government job, and they knew it comes with
some perks—no one can take it away from them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Monday, I reached LB Road in Adyar and walked past a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Mahindra_Bolero&quot;&gt;Bolero&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Toyota_Fortuner&quot;&gt;Fortuner&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to enter into the
office on the ground floor. I grew an inch shorter as I realized, no one really
cared what entered their office. Everyone where busy with their &lt;em&gt;work&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I felt
like a ghost, or should I say, the invisible man?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I slowly assessed who might be least annoyed, when I disturb them. Sitting right
next to the entrance was a person, slightly older than me, looking busily at
some files—I decided he would be my best bet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, I want to enquire about vacant land tax...&amp;quot;, I said, approaching him. He
cut me off replying, &amp;quot;Give the letter to him&amp;quot;. He was pointing to the desk in
the centre of the room. There were a few people standing there and one of them
was doing all the talking. Happy that I did not take more of the officer&#x27;s
precious time, I approached the clerk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;No, no form. Just give a letter.&amp;quot;, he said. &amp;quot;Attach a copy of the sale deed and
patta. And don&#x27;t forget to attach the EC&amp;quot;. EC stood for Encumbrance Certificate,
a document that provides the list of transactions pertaining to a specific
survey number. Proud that I already knew that, I returned home.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only then it struck me, that I did not know, whom the letter needs to be
addressed to. I went through the documents that I had, and the SOP mentioned the
&lt;em&gt;Assistant Revenue Officer&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in a number of places—I decided he was my man.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;request-for-property-tax-assessment.odt&quot;&gt;Here is the format of the letter I had
used&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, in case you find it useful. Use
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.libreoffice.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LibreOffice&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to open and edit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put all the documents in a green, cloth-lined envelope and carried an
additional copy of the letter that I could get dated, stamped and signed by the
clerk as an acknowledgement. This is the SOP that needs to be followed when
submitting documents to the government—I had learnt this from my father.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What Sir, should I do all the work? Take the letter out of the envelope and
give it to me. Write your name and phone number on the top&amp;quot;, said the letter
clerk when I gave it to him.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, sure&amp;quot;, I removed the documents, underlined my name and phone number
that were already there on the letter and handed them to him. I was
proud of my forethought, &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter clerk duly dated, stamped and signed my acknowledgement copy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, when will it be ready?&amp;quot; I asked sheepishly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir is in a meeting. He will call you&amp;quot;, he replied. I glanced furtively at the
designation on the board outside Sir&#x27;s room. It said—Assistant Revenue Officer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After submitting the letter, I waited for 2 more weeks. I did not have much hope
for any SMS as mentioned in the SOP. But I wanted at least, half of the SLA to
be past, before I ask for the status—I didn&#x27;t want to annoy the officers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to the Zonal office once again and enquired with the letter clerk.  &amp;quot;Sir,
just left now. All the officers are having a meeting in the Ripon building. You
do one thing. Call this number. He is the assessor. He will tell you the
amount&amp;quot;, he replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I called the assessor, and he asked to come by the local corporation office at
Brindavan Nagar Main Road the next day. When I reached there, only his assistant
was present.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What is the area?&amp;quot;, he grabbed the calculator lying on his desk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, tax will be for the entire 7 years&amp;quot;, he proceeded to calculate the amount
and pointed to the numbers that showed up on its liquid crystal display.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You have to give a DD for the amount. Only after you give the DD, we can enter
into the system. Call Sir.  He will tell you the correct amount.&amp;quot;, he concluded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thanked him and moved to a bench away from his desk and called the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Did you send the letter by post?&amp;quot;, he asked. &amp;quot;Ah… OK. I haven&#x27;t received the
documents yet from Adyar. I will call you once I get it.&amp;quot;, he said, ending the
call.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back home, nervously waiting for the call. The assessor called after a few
days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What is the plot number? Where does the Sri Krishna Nagar come?&amp;quot;, he asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sir, it is an unapproved layout and your department is no longer using the
original name.&amp;quot;, I replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;OK, can you submit a copy of the parent sale deed where the plot number is
mentioned?&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes&amp;quot;, I replied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day after, I took the document copies to the Brindavan Nagar Main Road
office and gave it to the assistant. &amp;quot;Sir, is in Velachery office. I will give
it to him, when he comes by&amp;quot;, he said.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some chit-chat, he hinted, &amp;quot;I don&#x27;t know when the assessor will come. If
you want, I can go and give the documents in Velachery today itself.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sensed in his voice, the hope of making a few hundred rupees to indulge in his
favourite vice. I was not going to fall for his sweet talk. &amp;quot;Sir said, he will
collect it when he comes by&amp;quot;, I replied firmly.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• • •&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Your tax will be Rs. 23,200&amp;quot;, the assessor finally called around a week later,
quite late in the evening. &amp;quot;Bring a DD for the amount tomorrow.&amp;quot;, he reminded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the same amount that the clerk showed on the calculator. Until now, I
had not given any bribe to the assessor. Neither did he ask for it. I wanted to
see, how far I could hold.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, why did he ask for a DD? The SOP clearly said that the assessor would raise
the notice for tax with the bill number, and we could pay it through a number of
channels including, online payment or swipe a card at one of the ward offices.
The amount that I had to pay was significant.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What if the assessor misused the DD or delayed the process after I give it to
him?&amp;quot;, I asked my mom in trepidation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Government officers will not do such things&amp;quot;, she assured.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounded very naive, but 35 years of experience in the education department
of the Tamil Nadu State Government, should count for something.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;He will write your name and the bill number in the back of the DD&amp;quot;, she
assured. This sounded like a better advice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I will write my name myself&amp;quot;, I said, happy that the DD cannot be
misused to pay tax for someone else.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor could still, simply deny receiving the DD, while still raising the
bill. But this would only be an attempt to spite me, and he could not personally
profit from it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I decided to leave nothing to chance. &amp;quot;I will take a photo copy of the DD and
get it signed by the assessor as an acknowledgement&amp;quot;, I declared.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day, I took the DD and hurried to the corporation office and
forgot to take a photo copy and also to write my details in the back of the DD.
How stupid of me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor took the DD, wrote my name and phone number in the back and put it
in his drawer. &amp;quot;The bill will be ready in a day or two. You will receive an SMS.
You can come and collect the receipt from the office.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not hint on any bribe, but his demeanour was cold and impersonal.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still cursing myself for not having taken a photo copy and was a little
worried. But decided to leave it at this and call the assessor only after a
couple of days. Soon, I got busy with other work and on the second day, I got a
call from the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Your bill is ready. Collect it from the Velachery corporation office&amp;quot;, he said.
&amp;quot;Yes, it is near the Dhandeeswaram temple in Velachery.&amp;quot;, he further directed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was familiar with the place but never knew that a corporation office existed
there. I asked a local person on reaching the place, and he pointed to the
building, which is not easy to miss, once you start looking for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going inside the building, past the trees, I saw a typical government office,
with a building in faded yellow, or was it blue? I cannot remember. There was a
shed being repaired in the front.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessor was sitting behind a counter with a computer. &amp;quot;This must be his
primary work location&amp;quot;, I said to myself. He was on the phone with someone, but
on seeing me, he printed a copy of the bill, stamped and signed it, while
still multitasking on the phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I missed adding the late fee. You need to pay that also&amp;quot;, he said after
finishing the phone call. It amounted to a few hundred rupees.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Can I pay it by cash?&amp;quot;, I asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;There is no work for cash after this. Everything is online. If you have a card,
you can swipe in the machine here&amp;quot;, the assessor replied, pointing to the desk
by his side.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took out my debit card and gave it to his assistant who was at the swiping
machine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feeling happy at the turn of events, I thanked the assistant and the assessor
for their work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;YOU COME AND GO SO MANY TIMES FOR THIS WORK, but you never think of giving us
something for our expenses. GIVE AT LEAST 1000 TO HIM&amp;quot;, the assessor finally
let his frustration out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was feeling ashamed on hearing it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked the person to come outside the office. There I took two Rs. 500 notes
and gave it to him. Emotions of shame, pity and thankfulness suppressed the
analytical side of my brain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;• • •&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking through this episode now, I could have saved myself a lot of work and money
by going directly to the assessor, dropping the letter along with a Rs. 500
note, like a professional.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But would that improve things? No.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should still give the application in the Zonal office, where I get an
acknowledgement with the date of submission. It is likely that the SLA of 30
days is being tracked, which is why the assessor finished the work without me
pushing for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should also insist on online transfer or card payment instead of the DD. Even
if it meant bribing the assessor.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if my mom is true, and government officers do not commit fraud, at least
for such small amounts, the DD business gives undue power to the officers in
addition to being cumbersome. All three must be put to an end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Trouble with Sarathi</title>
		<published>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/trouble-with-sarathi/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/trouble-with-sarathi/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I had to renew my wife&#x27;s driving licence which was issued at Tindivanam RTO.
Unfortunately, it was not uploaded into the computerized records at the time it
was issued, and it was a prerequisite for renewing the licence from a different
RTO other than the one where it was issued.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On enquiring at a local driving school, they asked to visit the concerned RTO
and request them to upload the details into the system. Half done digitization,
and countless hours of human life wasted, with each person having to make a request
individually!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited the RTO in person and the letter receiving clerk asked to write a
letter as he is wont. Accepting the letter and a copy of the licence, he
dismissed me saying that I will receive an SMS in a week or so after it is
uploaded.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never got any SMS even after 2 weeks. On checking the driving licence in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sarathi.parivahan.gov.in&#x2F;sarathiservice&#x2F;stateSelection.do&quot;&gt;Parivahan Sarathi portal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, it
showed an application number, and it was pending approval.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another visit to the RTO, this time, by my father-in-law and the answer was that
there was some delay in the server, and they would upload it in a few days.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, I never received any SMS after that, and without a proper way of
knowing the status, I was resigned to have someone visit the RTO once again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to check the status one last time, before the imminent visit, but the
site was frustratingly slow. I even disabled &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;UBlock_Origin&quot;&gt;uBlock
Origin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
suspecting that some &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; bloatware was causing problems. But still the
website was slow. Finally, when I got to the view the status, it showed that the
application was blocked on me for uploading the required documents. When I tried
to upload them, it errored out and the site hanging on every step was
making it even more difficult to figure out why I got the error.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of frustration, I decided to dig a bit deeper into the site, and
opened the Web Developer Tools on Firefox. I was able to see calls to
&lt;em&gt;vani-hyd.nic.in&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; hanging and timing out after a few minutes—this was the
reason the website was slow. I also realized, this might not be a critical
part as, after time out I was able to proceed to further steps. On
right-clicking the URL in the request list, I noticed that there was an option
to block it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was exactly what I needed! I was excited by the possibility of me
finally completing my part of the application process—uploading the documents.
On finishing that step, it still errored. Cursing the software developers who built the
website, I began reading the page more attentively. Hidden in the verbiage of
instructions, it was mentioned that the file size should be less than 500 KB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick processing step with Ghostscript brought the file size down, within
limits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;gs -sDEVICE=pdfwrite -dCompatibilityLevel=1.4 -dPDFSETTINGS=&#x2F;ebook -dNOPAUSE -dQUIET -dBATCH -sOutputFile=output.pdf input.pdf
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it was all smoothing sailing and the upload process succeeded, though it
abruptly landed on the initial status request page without any mention of the
happy news. I had to once again key the application number and the captcha to
find the updated status—further actions were on the RTO.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t think everyone would be able to complete this step without
seeking assistance from a third party like a driving school. Looks like Digital
India instead of improving things, has just added another layer of
private intermediaries between the government and the citizen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process took another 3 weeks, where my computer skills didn&#x27;t help, and my
father-in-law had to still visit the RTO to prod the officers into action. The
clerk was kind enough to give his phone number, so that, we could remind him
over the phone, instead of a direct visit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only nice part of the whole process was that, there was no direct ask for a
bribe to speed things up. The clerk and the officer were trying to genuinely
complete the process, though hampered by inefficient systems and their lack
of skill.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>No poo and some more</title>
		<published>2024-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-08-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/no-poo/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/no-poo/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started having excessive dandruff starting from my teen ages. The obvious solution at
that time was to switch from &lt;em&gt;Clinic Plus&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Head and Shoulders&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; for my weekly
hair wash, which we called, the head-bath. The day of the head-bath, everything
looked spick-and-span, but the next day, my whole head was filled with scales of dead skin. Soon, my favourite
pastime became, taking a newspaper and combing my dandruff onto it and
wondering in bewilderment at the amount of skin I had shed. Applying coconut oil
made the flakes gooey, like oversoaked breakfast cereal. Skipping it made it
look fresh, ready to be thrown it into a bowl.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little did I know, that, the shampoo was making the problem worse, by taking away
the natural oil layer secreted by the skin. The skin panics on detecting this loss and secretes more
of its oil, which becomes a bumper food supply for the fungus on our skin, which
grow exponentially, triggering the skin cells to molt
in profusion. Ignorant of this complexity,
I increased the frequency of shampoo use and ended up with just a bigger
dandruff mound on the newspaper.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=EmiqG_XdePY&quot;&gt;a video by &lt;em&gt;Dave
Hakkens&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&#x27;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which introduced me to
the &lt;em&gt;No Poo&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; movement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stopped using shampoo, or for that matter even our traditional alternatives
like &lt;em&gt;shikakai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Instead I started washing my hair daily with just plain water and
also skipped applying coconut oil, in an attempt to deprive the fungus of fatty oils. After a few months things looked better. The
absence of, the day-after-the-head-bath flare-up, itself, was a big relief. I have continued this with
good success for maybe 10 years now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also the period when I slowly moved away from hot water to unheated water
for bathing. This also likely helped reduce the stress on the skin as hot water
can remove natural skin oils more, than cold water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cold water for bathing was something that I dreaded from my childhood. There was
this children&#x27;s magazine called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wisdom.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wisdom&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; where I had read
that bathing in cold water is the best for the human body. In spite of this, I
could never make this a habit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from my home to my college in Pondicherry was a 3 hour journey that I
used to make almost every week and invariably it was a Monday morning. I had to
bath at around 4:30 AM, and hot water was what I used. Even then, by the time I
reached college, I had sweated so much during the bus journey, that I felt 
uncomfortable sitting in the class, I even started walking all the way to the
hostel to take a cold shower and walked back to the college, sometimes being
late or skipping the first hour. During this time I
tried experimenting with taking bath in cold water instead of hot water,
before I started from home on the bus journey. Remarkably I sweated much less
and felt more fresh when I reached college.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with this, first-hand proof, it was more than 10 years later, that cold
showers became a habit.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I started skipping during this time, was, using bathing soap. I know, this
might be shocking and you might feel uneasy coming close to me, after knowing
this fact, but no one has complained to me, yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the &lt;em&gt;No Poo&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; process, I do not use any traditional replacements like
moong dal powder or the other umpteen things which people have suggested.
Initially I just used &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Luffa&quot;&gt;dried ridge gourd
sponge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to scrub my skin, but after a few months I started using it less
frequently. Now, I use the soap or the scrub very rarely, only in case I want to remove things like
oil, glue, paint or cement that are stuck to my skin. Otherwise, I just make good use of my hand
fingers and nails and in the process realizing how inflexible my hands were in
reaching my back. I also made good use of the towel I used to dry myself and
felt that the soap is better used on it than my body.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the daily cold water head-bath regimen running successfully, I did notice
that there was still some amount of dandruff and I realized, the daily head bath
may not be necessary. So now, I have switched to just a weekly head bath or sooner if I felt they were dirty. In
addition, I apply a bit of coconut oil on the hair after the head bath, as it
reduces the oil secreted by my scalp even more and keeps the fungus under
control. Now everything seems to be in a steady state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Wow, so, are the people who invented shampoo and soaps, fools?&amp;quot; I hear people ask.
If they have no use, how did they
get so popular? I suppose, they served a very narrow purpose when they were
invented. These were likely game changing and so they became popular, but soon they were being used even when they
were not necessary. Shampoo and soap are still the most advertised products on
television, serving very much as a proof that, only unnecessary products are
advertised. Antibiotics, paracetamol, sugar, fertilizers, the over-used-products list may just be growing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still fancy myself thinking, the marketing team of Procter and Gamble got word
of my findings and has spent crores of rupees &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=TMGQXeN6iqg&quot;&gt;on this
ad&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to shame me back into using their
product. &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Dandruff thirumba varave varathu&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, they plead, with the sincerity of a
car salesman.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Garudan</title>
		<published>2024-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/garudan/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/garudan/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Really enjoyed the movie &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Garudan_(2024_film)&quot;&gt;Garudan&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with another splendid performance by Soori, after &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Viduthalai_Part_1&quot;&gt;Viduthalai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. A must watch!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Passwords</title>
		<published>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-07-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/passwords/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/passwords/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Passwords are the simplest way for remote services to authenticate us and they
are ubiquitous. With the
number of online services we use, we try to cope by reusing passwords or making
them simple enough for us to remember. Both of these are big security risks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mitigate the friction of setting up passwords, many of the online services
allow to login using your Google or other major service providers. This is
technically secure, but has the risk that, if for some reason, Google determines
that you have violated their usage policy, you might end up not only &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.jefftk.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;how-likely-is-losing-a-google-account&quot;&gt;getting
locked out of your Google
services&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but
also, the entire Internet. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Google Chrome and Firefox store passwords automatically in the
browser and sync them with other devices. This also would pretty secure, except
they don&#x27;t provide explicit control over the files where the passwords are saved
or an explicit way to back them up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I have been using the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;keepassxc.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KeePassXC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
software which saves account passwords and additional information in a single
encrypted file which is unlocked using a master passwords. You still need to
remember a strong master password, but remembering a few strong passwords should
not be very difficult. In fact, it is similar to reusing the same
passwords across multiple services, in terms of ease of use, but is much more
secure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also store this file in a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.dropbox.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; folder which
allows syncing with my desktop, laptop and my Android phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the desktop I actually use &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.gnome.org&#x2F;Secrets&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Secrets&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which
works with the KeePass file format and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.keepassdx.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KeePassDX&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on Android. On iOS you can use
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.apple.com&#x2F;us&#x2F;app&#x2F;strongbox-password-manager&#x2F;id897283731&quot;&gt;Strongbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to ensure that, you don&#x27;t lose your passwords on any accidental
corruption, I have setup periodic backups of the password file using
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apps.gnome.org&#x2F;PikaBackup&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Pika&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on my desktop. The backups are done
to a Dropbox folder, and so, my backups reside on both my desktop and the
Dropbox cloud.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this setup may look more tedious than letting the browser store your
passwords and sync them, it gives me more confidence when I explcitly see where
things are stored.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Andhra Pradesh Community managed Natural Farming</title>
		<published>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/apcnf/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/apcnf/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apcnf.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Andhra Pradesh Community managed Natural Farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or
APCNF project is the only active government run natural farming program I could find in
India. They have a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;@APZBNF&quot;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that has a
large number of videos showing the principles and practices that are recommended
to farmers, but most of them are in Telugu. Even though I follow a bit of
it, I was not able to get the full details of specific procedures they recommend
to the farmers. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;nfcoalition.in&#x2F;people&#x2F;t-vijay-kumar&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Vijay Kumar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, who
heads the APCNF organization, has promised in one of the webinars held recently, that,
the content will soon be translated to
English for the benefit of people from the other states of India. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most valuable finds from the APCNF channel was the lecture by Walter
Jehne, an Australian microbiologist and cliamtologist, on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=GaXR3zLIM1U&quot;&gt;Regenerative
Agriculture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. His theory is that the
natural systems like soil and forests have kept the climate in a steady state
through millions of years through the natural process of rainfall and
transpiration. The destruction of forests and soil to acquire land for modern
industrial scale agriculture has had more impact on global temperatures than
increase in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sub&gt;. By restoring these systems, we can bring down global
temeperatures. Also restoring the soil goes a longer way in capturing rainfall
than building dams and other irrigation projects. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APCNF itself uses these theories and applies them to the farming practices
followed by actual farmers which is were the real test lies. For a short
overview on APCNF, I would recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;afsafrica.org&#x2F;wp-content&#x2F;uploads&#x2F;2022&#x2F;10&#x2F;natural-farming-guide-digital-lr.pdf&quot;&gt;this booklet called Taking Agroecology to
Scale&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by an organisation called Alliance for Food Sovereignty in Africa (AFSA), which
had studied APCNF with the goal of applying the learnings in Africa.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own journey in farming has been influenced till now by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Masanobu_Fukuoka&quot;&gt;Masanobu
Fukuoka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;G._Nammalvar&quot;&gt;Nammazhvar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;resources&#x2F;a045e67c-53fa-4ff9-be2a-f24707d41b58&quot;&gt;Roland
Bunch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and my own experience battling the &lt;em&gt;arugampul&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (Cynodon dactylon) ridden
compacted soil for the past 1.5 years (since January 2023).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, I have collected my thoughts on the APCNF principles and how I can
integrate them into my own practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;365 days of ground cover&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that having something growing throughout the year maximizes the
capture of solar energy and adds more biomass to the soil. But this is also
important for keeping the soil life alive and ready for the next crop. Also, soil with
growing plants capture more of the rain water than barren soil.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge in my land is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;supplying the required soil
moisture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for
growing crops througout the year. The well on my farm has sufficient water for
irrigation only during January to March, which is after the heavy North East
monsoon during the months from October to December. There are a few scattered
showers during the months of April and May, but they are not sufficient to
establish any new crop. The South West monsoon which starts in June, brings
intermittent rainfall, but I haven&#x27;t been able to retain enough moisture for a
successful crop in 2023 without additional irrigation. During the NE monsoon
season of 2023, I had the reverse
problem of water stagnation on my bunded field. I had missed to promptly drain
the fields after the bouts of heavy rains.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to identify crops that are suitable for each of these
seasons. A crop that is already established during during January and February
can withstand the hot and dry months of March to May. So intercropping a short
duration crop and a longer duration crop could be a solution.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sequence of crops is also important. For example, it is better to
grow a grain or food crop after &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;search-for-mucuna&quot;&gt;mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as it leaves the
field rich with nitrogen and reduced weed growth. Also, I am hoping that as the
soil structure improves, it can percolate more of the rain water allowing plant
growth during the dry spells.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also need to find an alternative to mucuna which
requires lesser water, as I will not have sufficient water for irrigation if I
increase the land under cultivation. Canavalia (&lt;em&gt;thamattai avarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil), is
supposed to be more drought tolerant than mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diverse crops including trees&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi cropping i.e. growing more than one crop in the same field is a big part
of APCNF&#x27;s recommendation. This is not just a legume and a grain intercopped,
but 8 to 12 species grown together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is surely a challenge to grow so many varied crops in the same field close
together, even though I do everything with just manual labour. Harvesting
becomes more complex and I have to go through multiple passes, picking each of
the crop separately. Some crops like
mucuna cannot be grown together with other crops as they grow aggresively and
bury other plants below their lush growth, if there is sufficient water for them
to grow. Similarly, I have seen &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;horse-gram&quot;&gt;Horsegram&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; also smother other
plants.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big part of this recommendation is growing trees along with field crops.
The trees supposedly provide shade and reduce evaporation of moisture
from the top layers of the soil. This would be useful especially during
the months from March to May when it might not be possible to have field crops
growing due to lack of water, whereas the trees with deeper roots would continue
to be growing. The trees can be pruned before establishing the next crop in June
or July to provide adequete sunshine for the field crop. The leaves and small
branches from the pruned trees can be used as mulch. This technique is also
called Alley cropping i.e. growing field crops between hedged rows of trees and is a
well established practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on this,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to determine compatibility matrix of each crop with the others.
From this, I need to create guilds of crops that can be grown together.
Combining this with the seasonal elements is going to be interesting.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to find the perennial trees and long duration plants that can be
grown on the hedge rows. I think it might be difficult to grow fruit trees in this manner as the field
crop is going to get the higher priority in terms of when the tree will be
pruned. Leguminous trees like &lt;em&gt;Agathi&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Sesbania_grandiflora&quot;&gt;Sesbania
grandiflora&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Gliricidia&quot;&gt;Gliricidia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are a good option.
I also plan to expriment with trees that are naturally dispersed in my field like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Azadirachta_indica&quot;&gt;Neem tree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pencil Maram&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Acacia_auriculiformis&quot;&gt;Acacia auriculiformis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Borassus_flabellifer&quot;&gt;Palm tree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Timber
trees like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Teak&quot;&gt;Teak&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are also be a good
option.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another interesting technique I intend to follow is called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;resources&#x2F;bb74e905-3feb-4c87-9638-1b4f028cd778&quot;&gt;Farmer Managed
Natural
Regeneration&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
This is the technique where the farmer nurtures and grows the tree saplings
that naturally popup every year all over the field and were sown by birds,
squirrels and other animals. What a joy it is, to work with nature! 
If left to nature, it is very much capable of turning the land into
robust forest in a decade, but we then lose our ability to grow
field crops. So we still need to decide
which saplings and how many, we nurture and which ones we destroy. This
technique doesn&#x27;t create neat rows of trees like in alley cropping, but
the trees end up disperesed all over the field. Nevertheless, the utility
should still be the same with no major disadvantages.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No&#x2F;low till&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the key principles of Fukuoka and the primary technique which
pulled me into farming. I have clearly seen, from my experience, how tilling destroys
&lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;hello-earthworm&quot;&gt;the soil structure that nature had tirelessly built&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But starting from a compacted soil, it is very difficult to grow the first few
years of crop. Usually it is recommended to start with a well tilled field
without grass or weeds and follow no till from the second year onwards. For some
reason, I am not inclined to do it. Maybe, I want to prove the power of nature in restoring even a
compacted degraded soil without fossil fuel inputs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only disturbance I am doing is to dig a 1 feet wide trench every 1.5 meters
which I use for irrigation and also as a drainage mechanism during
rains. I use the soil from the trenches to form the tall bunds which demarcate
the fields and retain the water. The trenches can also be used to hold excess biomass
after laying out as mulch on the beds. The trenches are dug perpendicular to the
slope of the land and slows down the flow of water and helps in percolation.
It also provides a path to walk within the field for inspection
and harvesting. In effect the field looks like parallel rows of raised beds, which
makes the job of sowing a lot more cumbersome than broadcasting on flat
rectangular field.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to perform a true Fukuoka style broadcast sowing using
seed balls. I am forced to hoe down the grass atleast an inch or two after I
broadcast, without which the seeds do not have sufficient contact with the
soil and are likely to be eaten away. Also hoeing kills the weeds and
without which there is too much competition for the crop to get established.
This is a back breaking work and is not scalable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been fascinated by Krishna McKenzie&#x27;s technique of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=y0xmEDq3NIs&quot;&gt;sowing rice
over a cover crop of mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Mucuna forms a dense layer of vegetation which suppresses grass and other
weeds and the crop grown after, is able to establish quickly without much
competition. The effort in preparing the soil by hoeing and drilling the seeds is greatly reduced.
We simply broadcast the seeds over the growing mucuna plants and then we enter the field to
cut the vines and shake it to ensure the seeds reach the soil and lay the cut vines over it. There is
sufficient disturbance when pulling at the vines and stepping on the soil, to lightly bury
the seeds. The leaf litter and vines also cover the seeds to hide them
from birds and also decay quickly to form an additional layer of rich soil over the seeds.
Also the crop gets to use the nitrogen fixed by mucuna,
in addition to the nitrogen from the decaying green leaves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already tried this over one season, but had to still hoe to
remove the weeds that refused to be suppressed. I was also not confident that the
seeds would get buried enough to have proper germination. I think over the
years, the weed pressure should reduce so that I can skip the hoeing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to monitor the effort needed to sow on these raised beds vs a flat
field. There are tradeoffs between sowing effort and the better irrigation
between the two.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to perfect the technique of sowing over a cover crop of mucuna as a scalable
mechanism for planting and weed control. I should try this out with other
grains like bajra and ragi and also experiment with other cover crops like
canavalia, instead of mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to really evaluate if making seed pellets is worth the effort
compared to sowing over mucuna. This will allow me to have two continous crops
instead of having to reserve one crop for mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrate animals into farming&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Animals require more active care and constant human presence. I want to
establish a farming practice where I would only be present on the farm for a few
days of the week. If I had farm animals, I would have to employ someone who
needs to stay with the animals 24&#x2F;7. This complicates the whole model. This
might be something I might consider later, but I decided to avoid using animals
for now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still get dung from cows that the villagers graze on the uncultivated
parts of my land and also the adjacent land. The villagers do collect the manure
dropped and take it with them to their own fields, but, I have been able to
collect some for myself and have experimented with making crude &lt;em&gt;Jeevamurtham&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
that I add to the irrigation water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manavari Velanmai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a traditional agriculture practice, where the farmer tills
the soil and sows the seeds before the rain and comes back to the field only to
harvest. So, there are precedences for avoiding constant presence in the farm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do fancy growing hens, but it needs to wait until I have the food grain
business going sustainably.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use of bio stimulants&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APCNF recommends adding solid and liquid bio-stimulants made from manure and
plant carbohydrates and also making Fukuoka style &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=X0cxJ9shbcI&quot;&gt;seed
pellets&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; treated with the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, I have made a bit of crude Jeevamrutham, but could not see visible impact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting good quantity of clay for making the pellets has been a challenge. I have made small
quantities of clay by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=ca20JkKFAcE&quot;&gt;dissolving the soil from my farm in water and letting the
water drip out of the solution through something like a cheese
cloth&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. But could not find an easy
way to grind the dried clay blocks to a powder to use in the pelletization
process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this forward,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to find a good way
to grind the processed dry clay and expriment with pelletization, atleast on a
small scale.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to evaluate the effectiveness of these bio stimulants in a more
appropriate scenario. I also need to experiment using the palm fruit as a free 
sugar source for making these bio stimulants.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crop residue and mulch&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This matches Fukuoka&#x27;s method of leaving the crop residue as a mulch over the
broadcasted seeds. I have clearly noticed the soil below the mulch retain
moisture better than the bare soil. This is also a key part of the Green Manure
Cover Crop practice advocated by Roland Bunch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximizing the organic matter production is a key requirement for this. I am
using cover crops like mucuna and sunn hemp purely for organic matter
production, although I don&#x27;t have any other uses for them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to evaluate more dual purpose crops, which produce food in
addition to large amount of bio mass. Some crops to try, include, Canavalia
(&lt;em&gt;thamattai avarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil) which looks to be bit more palatable than
mucuna and pigeon pea (&lt;em&gt;tuvarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil) which is similar to sunn hemp in
growing in poor soil and withstanding drought.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Farmer&#x27;s own seed or local seeds&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is very import to make farming self reliant without any external input,
but, having sufficient quantity of seed stock of the right variety needed for
the season is difficult. Selling seeds on a small scale is made more difficult
by a number of laws that purport to maintain seed
quality. So the farmer needs to maintain their own robust seed bank. Vialbility
also reduces when stored for multiple years, along with insects
attacking the seeds. So the seeds need to be regularly replaced with fresh
seeds from growing crops.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have started out with buying most of my seeds from the local agricultural
supply stores around Tindivanam. These are likely commercial varieties that
might be bred to take advantage of chemical inputs. I haven&#x27;t tried
heirloom seeds yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been able to replenish my seed bank with my own seeds for mucuna and sunn hemp, but doing it for the
food crops like, green gram, cow pea etc. has been difficult as I end up storing
the seeds incorrectly leading to insect atack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a more disciplined storage method and a way to track their age.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to study the characterstics of different varities of the same crop
to select seeds suited for my climate, soil and the style of natural farming
that I perform.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest &amp;amp; disease management through botanical ingredients&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not faced any significant crop loss due to pest attack, likely because,
the yield is already low due to other reasons. Also, it is said that, the pests
attack only weak crops and when external
fertilizers, either manure or artificial, is added, weak crops crowd out the
field over the hardy ones and later end up getting attacked by pests. This leads
to significant crop loss compared to just letting these weak crops die early and
letting the hardy crops provide a lower yield.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I would be able to find right balance between the two.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strict NO to chemical inputs&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this is the easist principle to follow if you aren&#x27;t constrained by
needing high yields. In addition to saving money, chemicals like Glyphosate
which is used as a weedicide, pose a risk to human health. Here I prefer using
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Precautionary_principle&quot;&gt;precautionary
principle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of not using a
technique that has a risk of damaging
human health than waiting for it to be proven.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have learnt a lot from studying APCNF. Using it as a framework for evaluating my
current practice has given me a confidence that I am going in the right path and
given me a number of new ideas that I can try out and improve on. I now have a better
picture of what my end goal looks like in my journey to grow food without using
fossil fuels.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Cleaning your car</title>
		<published>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/cleaning-your-car/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/cleaning-your-car/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a learnt a lot on car maintaineance from my guru
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;@chrisfix&quot;&gt;ChrisFix&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. One of the basic lessons I had
was cleaning my car for daily use. Not any fancy detailing, but just like the daily
bath we have — getting rid of the dust and dirt from regular driving through the
day or week or just  being parked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see a number of people use different methods to clean their cars, and I get
horrified when I see some drivers using a dirty looking piece of cloth and buffing
around an expensive luxury car just before the owner gets in. Learning what to
do, to maintain the fresh look of the painted surfaces is important. Learning
what not to do is often more important. For, you can develop infinite capacity to
not do things, but are limited by time on the things to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is ChrisFix&#x27;s own advice on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=ef_-SNSnByg&quot;&gt;what not to do when cleaning your cars&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;ef_-SNSnByg?si=B7uaTmTe3X-lr3v7&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is the daily bath routine I follow for my car:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take two buckets of clean tap water.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take a clean, washed micro fiber towel.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rinse it in the first bucket of water.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fold it as many times as required to get a surface area that is size of the
palm of your hand so that you can use it comfortably.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clean your car in straight motions, picking up the dust and dirt and leaving a clean surface.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clean the top part of the car first and then move to the bottom areas which is dirtier.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As the area of the towel gets dirty, change the fold to expose a portion that
is not soiled yet and use it. Once one side of the towel is all used up, you can
change to the back side and fold it as before and use it.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once both side are dirty, rinse in the first bucket of water, and then another time in the second bucket.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the water in the first bucket turns dirty enough, usually around 2
rinses, Refill it and use it as the second bucket, while the earlier second
bucket with the less dirty water, becomes the first.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually I am able to clean a car that is standing for a week without use, using
two to three rinses of the towel and four buckets of water. I have used this
technique for the better part of 15 years and I am really impresed with the
shine that still remains on my car.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still here with me and this kind of thing excites you, move on to ChrisFix&#x27;s
magnum opus — &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=CFXfSBR5Q9w&quot;&gt;How to Super Clean Your Car&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;CFXfSBR5Q9w?si=_GfZkECo1Erskkk8&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>@sunson</title>
		<published>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right from my school days when I started using the Internet, I had been
following people on the Internet, from whom I have continously learnt and shaped my
understanding of the world. Although it might sound a bit kitsch, I would compare this to the
relationship between &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Ekalavya&quot;&gt;Ekalavya and
Dronacharya&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but the comparison breaks
down when I gratefully recollect how much more I have received from my gurus than
what Ekalavya received from Dronacharya. And have I been as worthy a student as
Ekalavya? I don&#x27;t think so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these exemplary gurus and closest to my heart has been Suraj Kumar. I
remember, the first time I saw him was around 1998, in one of the ILUGC (Indian Linux User&#x27;s
Group - Chennai) meetings held regularly in the IIT Madras campus. He was the same age as
me, but vastly more knowledgeable and driven. I was this reticent Linux newbie
and was at
awe with the MoM&#x27;s he wrote after
each meeting - every detail captured in his pleasant style with a unique sense
of humour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued to follow his posts as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;@sunson on Live
Journal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;sunsonian&quot;&gt;@sunsonian on
Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The later half of the 2000s were the
heydays of Web 2.0 and
there were increasingly more options for staying connected and learning from my
gurus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I internalized a number of life changing concepts like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Peak_oil&quot;&gt;Peak
oil&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Emergence&quot;&gt;Emergence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; through his writings and
the links he posted on the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Delicious_(website)&quot;&gt;Delicious bookmarking
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. He introduced me to
other communities like &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;theoildrum.com&#x2F;special&#x2F;archives&quot;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
which opened their own wide worlds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I was already an atheist, @sunson&#x27;s explorations and thoughts were much
deeper. He introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Richard_Dawkins&quot;&gt;Richard
Dawkins&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and I devoured his
books, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_Selfish_Gene&quot;&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_God_Delusion&quot;&gt;The God Delusion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest impact he had on me must be his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;sunson&#x2F;albums&#x2F;72157626205527503&quot;&gt;efforts at natural
farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I
eagerly followed his journey as he introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Masanobu_Fukuoka&quot;&gt;Masanobu
Fukuoka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s writings and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;G._Nammalvar&quot;&gt;Nammalvar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This had a great impact on my own journey into natural farming that I
started in January 2022.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like everything ends where it starts and I learn &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.freelists.org&#x2F;post&#x2F;ilugc&#x2F;ILUGC-Trichy,6&quot;&gt;from this post on the ILUGC mailing
list&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that @sunson is no longer
with us. In this ephemeral digital
age, I am thankful that the Internet Archive&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Wayback_Machine&quot;&gt;Wayback
Machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.archive.org&#x2F;web&#x2F;20231204190058&#x2F;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Live Journal
blog
archived&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
although his delicious bookmarks and his personal website are lost. The Twitter
feed anf Flickr photos hang on a noose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope his writings survive the bitrot and continue to educate and
inspire more of us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Darebee healthy</title>
		<published>2024-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/darebee-healthy/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/darebee-healthy/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After an acute spike in my blood sugar in November 2020, I embarked on a strict
process involving keto diet, intermittent fasting and strength training
exercises. More than 5 years before that, I was diagnosed with fatty liver which
I largely ignored and was visibly overweight, reaching 90 kgs. After the
intervention, I probably lost around 20 kg of weight and 4 inches in waist size
over a period of around a year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise was indispensible part of this process. Cost many times does indicate
quality, but when it comes to knowledge and learning, it is always a contra
indicator. What is costly is priced for the easy path shown to acheive a metric, which by requirement needs to be easily measured. But these metrics are only a proxy for the outcome that you desire, which only time can reveal. I was always wary of buying education. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I viewed my exercise journey as an education process and decided to seek out
high quality sources which aren&#x27;t manufactured specifically to sell to me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;@RowanRow&quot;&gt;Rowen Row&#x27;s channel on Youtube&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with mostly following this no equipment exercise routine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;9tT8afUt7kM?si=YPndX_pS7_rHW4ZV&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few months I wanted a bit more of variety and started on a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;playlist?list=PLLXmeIOBkPXRV32fch2mbJgHK8k0xu31n&quot;&gt;28 day
fitness program based on videos by a person called Ashley
Conrad&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
I still remember not being able to stand on one leg without holding on to a support when doing the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=YdB1HMCldJY&amp;amp;list=PLLXmeIOBkPXRV32fch2mbJgHK8k0xu31n&amp;amp;index=4&amp;amp;t=324s&quot;&gt;standing quadricep
stretch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
It is likely an early indicator of the neural damage which can lead to
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Parkinson%27s_disease&quot;&gt;Parkinson&#x27; disease&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. After more than 3 years of practise, I have gained my
balance.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the real world uses of strength is in fights and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Mixed_martial_arts&quot;&gt;Mixed Martial
Arts&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or MMA piqued my
interest. I enjoyed watching the fights and read through &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;6966926-the-ultimate-mixed-martial-arts-training-guide&quot;&gt;The Ultimate Mixed
Martial Arts Training
Guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by Dann Plyler. This talked more about the philosophy and techniques used. The book,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;1735237.Training_for_Warriors&quot;&gt;Trainig for
Warriors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by
Martin Rooney had a bit more on exercise routines and I diligently practised them
for a few months.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any good habit, it is easy break a streak and getting back on track is
difficult. I often lose interest and many times my thrifty thought of &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;exercise
is a waste of time and resources and instead I should rely more on manual work&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;,
takes over. Also now that I am in a far better shape, I am no longer motivated
enough to do the strenuous 1 hour sessions I used to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;darebee.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DAREBEE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; website helps a lot. I found
this a year back and it was my next stop after the MMA encounter. DAREBEE has bite
sized pages that focus on a specific theme and has  multiple difficulty levels.
These can also be conveniently downloaded as a PDF to help refer during
exercises, wherever you are. Now that I am familiar with the basic movements and
their functions, I no longer need complete videos. The wide
variety of the exercise collection and the interesting gamification in some of
them all help sustain the streaks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also whenever I am in this mixed mood of not wanting to exercise but also
feeling awful because I am not, I push myself to do 10 squats
and 10 pushups before my morning bath. This often helps me get back on
my streak.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A word of  caution: most body weight exercises have very little risk of injury
compared to external weights. But always listen to your body and not over exert.
Do sufficient warmup before your exercise and have sufficient breaks and rest
days, during and after
the exercise. You will hear this a lot from everyone, but it cannot be over
emphasized.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Killers of the flower moon and diabetes</title>
		<published>2024-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/killers-of-the-flower-moon-and-diabetes/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/killers-of-the-flower-moon-and-diabetes/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Killers_of_the_Flower_Moon_(film)&quot;&gt;Killers of the flower
moon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a long
slow movie about the predicament of the people of the Osage tribe after oil was
found on their land. This is based on real life incidents which took place in
Oklahama in the USA in the 1920s which was also part of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Killers_of_the_Flower_Moon_(book)&quot;&gt;Killers of the
Flower Moon: The Osage Murders and the Birth of the
FBI&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a number of threads in the film, but the main focus is on the humans
succumbing to greed. The thread that most struck me was something that many
people were surprised when I first mentioned it to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Osage people, as with all socities that did not use fossil fuels, had to
depend on human and animal labour for their survival. Both agriculture and hunting
provided an active lifestyle and kept them healthy. When oil was found on their
land, they were given royalties which they spent on cars, servants and other
riches which changed their lifestyle suddenly. Soon there was an epidemic of
diabetes which was followed by hordes of doctors helping &#x27;cure&#x27; it by trying out
the newly discovered insulin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds similar to our generation and our parents&#x27;?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why was there a stark effect on the Osage people when the white men also had
changes to their lifestyle due to oil and coal? I can only guess: the shift in
lifestyle happened more suddenly for these people and for centuries they
had to do more physical activity than the Europeans.
Coupled with the &#x27;free money&#x27; and the general loss of agency leading to addiction —
not just to liquor and other substances, but just simply the new food.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other people have also noticed this thread and have written about it. For example,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;medicine.yale.edu&#x2F;news-article&#x2F;what-the-killers-of-the-flower-moon-movie-teaches-us-about-historical-trauma-and-indigenous-health&#x2F;&quot;&gt;this article on the Yale: School of
medicine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;slate.com&#x2F;culture&#x2F;2023&#x2F;10&#x2F;killers-of-the-flower-moon-movie-mollie-burkhart-diabetes-indigenous-native-osage-history.html&quot;&gt;this one on the Slate&#x27;s
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
But I would surely like more publicity on the diabetes thread in this movie.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Desktop and Mobile Setup</title>
		<published>2024-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/desktop-setup/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/desktop-setup/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Setting up a new computer is always exciting, but when you have a number of
ongoing projects and work that quickly needs to be resumed without downtime, it
is worth standardizing and documenting the process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is my preferred computer desktop setup which I replicate on any new
machine I use:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS: Debian stable
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;wayland&#x2F;comments&#x2F;14hhath&#x2F;comment&#x2F;jpbynnv&#x2F;?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;amp;utm_term=1&amp;amp;utm_content=share_button&quot;&gt;enable higher resolutions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on my Acer EL220Q monitor:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edit &#x2F;etc&#x2F;default&#x2F;grub and set GRUB_CMDLINE_LINUX to &amp;quot;video=VGA-1:1920x1080@64.9&amp;quot;. In case this doesn&#x27;t work, try a lower refresh rate like @49.9.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &#x27;sudo update-grub&#x27; and reboot.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS: Windows when I am forced to
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;scoop.sh&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Scoop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; package manager for installing applications&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Desktop: Gnome with the following extensions:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;ubuntu&#x2F;gnome-shell-extension-appindicator&quot;&gt;Top Indicator App&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;fflewddur&#x2F;tophat&quot;&gt;TopHat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web Browser: Firefox with the following extensions:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;iorate.github.io&#x2F;ublacklist&#x2F;docs&quot;&gt;uBlacklist&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;gorhill&#x2F;uBlock&quot;&gt;uBlock Origin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gitlab.gnome.org&#x2F;World&#x2F;secrets&quot;&gt;Password Safe &#x2F; Secrets&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;keepassxc.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;KeePassXC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; when I am using Windows.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;settings&#x2F;ssh&#x2F;new&quot;&gt;Create new SSH key&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;git&lt;pre style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span&gt;git config --global user.email &amp;quot;arunkd13@gmail.com&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;git config --global user.name &amp;quot;Arunkumar Dhananjayan&amp;quot;
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IDE: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;code.visualstudio.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with following extensions:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vscodevim.vim&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vscode-org-mode.org-mode&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application Software:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.getzola.org&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;getting-started&#x2F;installation&#x2F;#debian&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.dropbox.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gnucash.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Gnucash&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.gimp.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Gimp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following is my mobile setup with my preferred apps:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS: Android&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apps
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.google.android.apps.nbu.files&quot;&gt;Files&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.dropbox.android&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.orgzly&quot;&gt;Orgzly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.android.keepass&quot;&gt;KeePassDroid&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.wunderground.android.weather&quot;&gt;Weather Underground&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;f-droid.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;F-Droid&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;f-droid.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;packages&#x2F;org.schabi.newpipe&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NewPipe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Keeping up with Youtube channels</title>
		<published>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/keeping-up-with-youtube-channels/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/keeping-up-with-youtube-channels/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;All &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Youtube&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; channels have a subscribe button, but
there is no good way for me to consume the videos from the channels once I have
subscribed to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youtube does show a list of all the subscribed channels on the left side bar. It
also shows a big list of all the videos from all my subscribed channels sorted
with the most recent at the top. But these become unweildy, once I have more
than a couple of subscriptions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any time, I am in the mood to watch videos only from a specific topic, while
the one-big-list has all of them mixed together. Channels that release videos
more frequently clutter the feed. This totally frustrates me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Youtube forces me to use the home screen where an algorithm or more likely an AI
selects what videos I can watch next. These videos are not just from the
channels I have subscribed, but a mish mash of videos that may or may not
contain new videos from my subscriptions. Interestingly, there are automatically
chosen topics using which I can filter the videos in the home screen, but they
never match how I want to group them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does Youtube know about these problems? Most likely. But I guess none of the
Product Managers and UX Designers at Youtube would dare to do anything about them.
Fixing them would basically mean giving more control to the viewers and power to
the channels through the direct connection it provides. Youtube as an intermediary,
would lose its ability to monopolize the video streaming market. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power that Youtube gets is turned directly into quarterly revenue. The
AI that decdes what videos I can watch next hyper-optimizes for the hours that I
spend on watching videos rather than what is good for my life. Google, Youtube&#x27;s
parent would care less. Google as a company would rather &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.wheresyoured.at&#x2F;the-men-who-killed-google&#x2F;&quot;&gt;kill its customers and
themselves in the long run, rather
than leave some revenue on the table in the short
term&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The side effect of this power is the addiction that it afflicts on the viewers
and the arbitrary censorship that it ends up doing as it editorializes the home
screen. This has been the pattern not just for Youtube, but Facebook and Twitter
too. I hear, newer video platforms like TikTok have simply foregone even the
illusion of a subscription mechanism.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google once had this motto called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Don%27t_be_evil&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Don&#x27;t be
evil&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which looks like has long
been officially removed. The trust and good will that Google had in its initial
days has been sold to the highest bidders. Products like the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Google_Reader&quot;&gt;Google
Reader&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are created and maintained
to choke other alternatives and suddenly sunset, once they have served their
purpose. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In such a hostile environment, there are still some places of refuge.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of them which I have personally used and like is the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;newpipe.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NewPipe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; Android app. This allows to search and browse
videos from channels and also group your subscriptions based on topics, so that,
you can have a more focussed video session catching up on a specific topic. I
still would like a few improvements on the video feed screen, but since it is
open source, I should be able to add them myself. Or I could even create my own
app using the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;TeamNewPipe&#x2F;NewPipeExtractor&quot;&gt;NewPipeExtractor&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; library,
which is part of the same project and used by NewPipe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since NewPipe is not very amenable to Google&#x27;s designs, it is not allowed on the
official Play store. But you can still install it directly from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;newpipe.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;their
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or from the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;f-droid.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;F-Droid app
store&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as explained in their home page. It might sound
daunting at first for someone who is not tech savy, but I promise, it is worth
the effort.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NewPipe also does not display any ads that you would see with the official
Youtube app or the website. This obviouly means, the channels lose the potential
revenue. This may sound like a bad thing, but in the long run, the high quality
channels will survive as people would be more willing to direcly fund them
through their website or other means. The low quality ones, might wither away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I think these pirate apps keep the ecosystem healthy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my attempt at the UX for catching up with my subscriptions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX for TVs&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;keeping-up-with-youtube-channels&#x2F;tv.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;UX for TVs&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX for mobile&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;keeping-up-with-youtube-channels&#x2F;mobile.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;UX for mobiles&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;edits&quot;&gt;Edits&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2024-04-26: Added link to the article on the degradation of Google Search to
increase ad revenue.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2024-04-23: Paraphrased text and added UX mockups.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Visualizing historical rainfall - Part 2</title>
		<published>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall-2/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall-2/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2023, I made a &lt;a href=&quot;visualizing-historical-rainfall.md&quot;&gt;visualization of the historical rainfall over my farm&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to help me improve my farming practice. This was made using the the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; tool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in 2024, Observable folks released the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;framework&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable Framework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
which is a Javascript framework that can be used to create standalone
visualizations and built into a static website. This sounded exciting and I decided to take another
stab at rainfall visualization using this framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see it embedded below.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;950&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also access the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;standalone website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;climate-dash&quot;&gt;source code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is available on Github.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Water on soil</title>
		<published>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/water-on-soil/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/water-on-soil/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of both rainfall and irrigation depend on the soil type, structure and the natural slope of the land. This is even more important for growing crops only with rain water. So having good intutive understanding of the action of water on soil is important for successful farming.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows live demonstrations of how water flows on different soil types and layers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;ego2FkuQwxc?si=fl8l_LETyKWh4vNo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video helped me reason the effectivenss of a no-till agriculture. Following are the thoughts I had when I watched this video:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggregated soil, is best for water penetration. Soil that is physically aggregated by plowing gets compacted after a one or two rains or irrgations. It forms a hard crust, which I have seen farmers manually break with a hoe before they irrigate, so that the irrigation is effective. Soil that is aggregated with organic matter, is held together with excrements from the soil life that act like glue and structure is not easily destroyed by water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregated soil needs to be at the top where rain falls and is not effective if it is buried below a layer of fine powdered or compacted soil. Also the pores and channels made by animals need to be exposed at the top. Disturbing the soil by shallow plouging or even a hoe closes these pores and channels. What aggregated soil that may remain below the plough line is ineffective.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic matter that is buried below the soil does not help water infiltration. Traditionally it resulted in rapid decomposition and release of nutrients, but as with all techniques that help with short term results, you are basically stealing from your future. Organic matter is best left at the top as a mulch where it aids water infiltration, provides natural protection for insects, worms and animals which improve the soil structure. It also shades the soil and provides a better environment for the creatures to thrive. Fertility build up takes more time in this scenario, but is more resilient and increases over time, instead of getting depleted as with ploughing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Sunn Hemp</title>
		<published>2024-04-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/sunn-hemp/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/sunn-hemp/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;search?q=sunn+hemp&quot;&gt;Sunn Hemp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, aka &lt;em&gt;Sanappai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil, is a leguminous green manure cover crop (GMCC), but cannot be used as food. It&#x27;s stem&#x27;s are a source of natural fibre, which are used for making ropes. I am using this crop mainly as a GMCC for the nitrogen it fixes and the biomass it generates. It also has a hard woody tap root, which I assume helps break compacted soil.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-season&quot;&gt;Planting Season&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunn Hemp takes around 4 to 4.5 months for the seeds to be ready for harvest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried this crop initially in April 2023, when I planted it on a field, which I had shallow ploughed with a rotavator attached to a tractor. I did not have irrigation facility in this area and the land did not capture sufficient moisture from the summer rains for the crop to grow. All of them withered after growing about half a feet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I then planted it on a 1 meter wide bed in May, where I was able to irrigate it. This crop grew well and I was able to harvest the seeds around September.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I again planted it in December 2024 and irrigated it through February March, which also has grown well and has formed green pods as of April 2024.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Sunn Hemp is said to grow well with minimal water, I want to develop this as a summer cover crop that I plant in March and irrigate it minimally. Right now I am using Mucuna during this period, which requires copious amount of water for irrigation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fertility-requirement&quot;&gt;Fertility Requirement&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunn Hemp grows well in degraded soil. The only requirement I have seen is that, it needs to be able to form sufficient root depth. For this the soil either should not be heavily compacted, or there should be sufficient irrigation until it is established.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-and-growth&quot;&gt;Planting and Growth&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not seen many insects or ants eating the Sunn Hemp seeds. So this can be easily sown by broadcasting and raking at a shallow depth and germinates within a week. The growth is slow for the initial 2.5 months, but is rapid after that, and reaches a height of more than 6 feet. Even if the plants are eaten by rabbits and pigs in the initial growth phase, it forms new branches and grows vigorously in the second phase.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plants grow tall and so, can easily be broken by heavy winds or animal movement. Establishing a dense cover can help prevent them from falling over.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-harvest-processing&quot;&gt;Post Harvest Processing&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#x27;t tried extracting fibre from the stems. I have only harvested the seeds to use them for the next crop. The pods mature a bit staggered. So picking them individually might increase the yield. But since they are small, it becomes very labour intesive, and so I cut the entire branch and dry them. Once they are dry, the branches can be beaten with a stick and stamped with the feet to dislodge the pods and the seeds within the pods.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I use this only as seed for the next crop, I just store the mixture of seeds and broken specks of the dry shell and do not bother with extensive winnowing to get clean seeds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the plant is allowed to bear seeds, the stems become woody and the biomass it generates is bit difficult to handle as a mulch. So it might be beneficial to cut this early as soon as it flowers and grow another stand separately for seeds. This is something I am yet to try.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Clearing Sewage Mains</title>
		<published>2024-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/clearing-sewage-mains/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/clearing-sewage-mains/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have used the technique I have described at the end, a couple of more times. Now I am starting to proactively check and do the treatment every year to avoid the surprise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we reconstructed our house, we decided to reuse the existing sewage connection. We were fed up with the bribes that we kept paying right from getting building plan approval to tea money for the local beat constable. We didn&#x27;t want to once again pay the councillor and other metro water officials for a new connection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this was an old line, it was more than probably 10 feet under the ground level. We had the option to either make the sewage chamber deep enough so that the outlet pipe enters horizontally into the chamber or make the chamber less deep, and use a long bend to make the outlet line enter vertically into the chamber like an L.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having heard of labourers getting asphyxiated when entering sewage chambers to clear a clog, I decided to go for the second option, i.e. reduce the depth of the chamber and instead use a vertical pipe for the remaining depth. This unfortunately was not the right thing to do–because clearing any clog becomes difficult. The device used to clear the clog is a series of mild steel rods that are screwed along in a chain and has a bit of flex, but does not curve tight enough for it to pass through the long bend. On the other hand, if the outlet pipe is horizontal, the larger dimensions of the chamber opening provides a sufficient bend radius for the clog clearing rod to be inserted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem was that, the old line did not connect to the nearest mains chamber on our street, but used an older pipeline that likely joined a chamber further down on the main road.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, we ended up with our first clog with the sewage overlowing from the chamber during heavy inflow during the mornings. We called a few private people, on the recommendation of a metro water worker, who regularly visits houses to add chlorine to the water sumps. They unfortunately did not have the right tools and were not able to do clear the line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we went to the local metro water office, where there was a register to enter complaints about blocked sewage lines. We added the entry there and the worker on watch helpfully gave chlorine tablet to add to overhead tank. The sewage workers came in two days and said, since the block is in the line to our house we had to pay them separately for the work. With the situation we were in, we agreed to pay what they asked.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they prepared to start work, I broke the news on the vertical entry of the sewage pipe. On hearing this, they complained that this is going to make their work difficult. &amp;quot;The pipe should always be horizontal&amp;quot;, they declared. I told them reasoning for the decision that I had took. &amp;quot;Why do you worry Sir, however deep the chamber is, we will enter it to clear the line&amp;quot;, they said. Given our predicament, we asked what the options were.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They asked for a big waste cloth and screwed it on to the segmented rod that they use for clearing the lines. Now using the cloth as a plunger, they inserted it into the pipe. The pipe was under a few feet of sewage that was standing in the chamber. Now, they used a pumping action to oscillate the water in the pipe which miraculously dislodged the clog and the water began to drain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a week, we saw sewage, once again, stagnate in the chamber and panicked. Given that it was not sustainable to call the sewage workers every week, I decided to take the problem into my own hands. I checked out a number of YouTube videos on clearing sewage lines. There were a number of techniques, but the simple chemical solution ala Drainex seemed to be the simplest for my skill and equipment level.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My theory was that, the clog was due to fat deposits that had not fully dissolved and had once again coalesced to reduce the flow. I had read about Sodium Hydroxide aka Caustic Soda beind used as a chemical agent to dissolve fat deposits clogging sewage pipes. This costed around Rs. 90 per kg vs Rs. 500 per kg for something like Drainex. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added around 1 kg of caustic soda and a bucket of hot water to the chamber before going to sleep. First thing in the morning, I eagerly opened the chamber to see the state. It had been around 6 hours from the time I had started the treatment. Now the water had drained completely from the chamber.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I can now maintain the sewage connection for life without having to get a new one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Horse Gram</title>
		<published>2024-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/horse-gram/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/horse-gram/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;search?q=horse+gram&quot;&gt;Horse gram&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, aka &lt;em&gt;Kollu&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil, has been the most difficult crop for me. It does not tolerate water logging and the seeds are difficult to separate from the pods. The growing period is 4 months which also increases the risk of unfavourable weather. In spite of this, it is worth growing, as it is a super food that we should add in our diet. Hopefully you get the strength of a horse after eating it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-season&quot;&gt;Planting Season&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had limited success with sowing in mid December, but some of the crop wasted away due to water logging from an unexpected heavy rain in January. The remaining crop did grow well with irrigation, as the north-east monsoon ended. I had also tried a summer crop planted in March and April, but it did not have good growth, likely due to poor soil and lack of moisture because of poor irrigation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fertility-requirement&quot;&gt;Fertility Requirement&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This grows well in degraded soils without any added fertilizers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-and-growth&quot;&gt;Planting and Growth&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dry seeds can be sowed in wet soil if you expect continued showers, or the dry soil can be irrigated after sowing. The seeds germinate in less than a week.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plant flowers after 2.5 months and are easy to miss as they are pale green in colour. It takes another month for the pods to mature and dry. Since all plants and all pods do not mature at the same time, you may still need to wait for a couple of more weeks, before you can harvest. Unlike other pulses like Green Gram where the pods can be picked, the whole horsegram plant needs to be uprooted, due to the pods being small and numerous.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-harvest-processing&quot;&gt;Post Harvest Processing&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pods along with the vines are sun dried on a tarp and beaten with a stick to separate the seeds. The dislodged seeeds and the shells are winnowed to separate each other. There can be considerable loses in the unshattered pods, which are difficult to even separate by hand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Green Gram</title>
		<published>2024-04-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/green-gram/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/crops/green-gram/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;search?q=green+gram&quot;&gt;Green gram&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, aka &lt;em&gt;Pacchai Payaru&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Paasi Payaru&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil, and &lt;em&gt;Mung&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Hindi, was the first crop I had planted, around January 2023. Till date this has also been the easist and one of the bountiful crops for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-season&quot;&gt;Planting Season&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best planting season has been the Margazhi pattam (December - January), at the end of the North East monsoon rains. It can handle a bit of water logging, even if the monsoon continues after the planting. This is unlike the horse gram which I had planted along with it, which decayed in the water due to a unexpected heavy rain in January.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greengram that I had planted in March &#x2F; April withered away, even though I had irrigated it once per week. It likely needs more water than this and is not suitable as a summer crop. It is also possible that a more fertile soil might have helped it handle the summer better. Something to experiment in the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fertility-requirement&quot;&gt;Fertility Requirement&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With added organice fertilizers, it surely would give a better yield, but, can give a reasonable yield even without it. The second year crop in 2024, planted in December yielded better due to more organic content and nitrogen in the soil, from the mucuna planted earlier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;planting-and-growth&quot;&gt;Planting and Growth&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The seeds can be planted directly without soaking in water, provided, the soil has sufficient moisture or if you will irrigate it immediately. The seeds germinate and seedlings, with two leaves, show up in less than a week.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plant flowers in 1.5 months and the green pods should show up in 2 months. The pods dry and turn black, in a week or so, and it should be ready for the first picking. The first flush of pods ripen over 2 weeks and you have more flowers and pods coming up thereafter, which you can continue to pick. The best yield is from the first two pickings. The yield and the quality of the pods reduces thereafter and might not be economical.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-harvest-processing&quot;&gt;Post Harvest Processing&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pods can be dried on a tarp under the sun and stamped with the feet to shatter the pods. Another technique is to put the pods in a sack, and with its mouth closed, gently beat it with a stick to shatter the pods. You may have to crush the remaining pods with your fingers to extract the last bit that refuse to shatter by the above methods.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, it can be winnowed to separate the seeds from the shattered shell. &lt;em&gt;Muram&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, as it is called in Tamil, is a traditional tool that is used to separate light husks or shells from the heavier seeds. It needs a bit of practice to use it, but is sufficient for home scale use. I have not tried larger scale machines at this point.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The output of the separation is the whole green gram with the green outer skin. This whole green gram can be directly used for cooking. Further removal of the outer skin and splitting the seed results in the yellow split gram known as &lt;em&gt;Payatham Paruppu&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil. This is conventionally used to make the famous &lt;em&gt;Ven Pongal&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; dish of Tamil Nadu.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Risk Disclosure on Derivatives</title>
		<published>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/disclosure/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/disclosure/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following disclosure was shown, when I logged into my ICICI Direct account. Usually I skip reading these disclaimers, but this time I took the time to read it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 out of 10 individual traders in equity Futures and Options Segment, incurred net losses.
On an average, loss makers registered net trading loss close to ₹ 50,000
Over and above the net trading losses incurred, loss makers expended an additional 28% of net trading losses as transaction costs.
Those making net trading profits, incurred between 15% to 50% of such profits as transaction cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: SEBI Study&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woah, this is pretty hard hitting. It is not just the loss makers who are losing money, but even the profit makers lose a major portion as transaction cost.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting that, this gets splattered all over the trading interface, like the smoking warning on cigarette packs, and yet, people continue to use them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Public Libraries in Chennai</title>
		<published>2024-04-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/public-libraries-in-chennai/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/public-libraries-in-chennai/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Libraries have always been a place that excited me. They laid out the wonders of the world — past, present and future — in an all you can eat buffet. When I was a kid, I fancied myself starting a lending library and catalogued all the books in my house, but atleast, I ended up reading almost all of them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the distractions available to today&#x27;s kids, books are their least preferred form of entertainment. They do get books from the neighborhood lending library, but they seem to be atleast 5 years behind the kind of books that they should be reading for their age.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public libraries as a concept is very noble, but they may sound irrelevant when you can get almost the entire world&#x27;s knowledge on the Internet. But no ebook can beat the physical book in terms of the humane interface they provide and continue to be costly for a voracious reader. Public libraries make this luxury, something that everyone can enjoy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to visit they Public libraries in Chennai to see their state and make them one of the places that my kids go by themselves to in the City.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;district-central-library&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;chennai.tnlla.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;District Central Library&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first public library that I went to, as a kid, in the 1990s. It had atleast 3 floors of books, then, and also a kids section. Now when I visited it in 2023, it was reduced to just the ground floor and the place looks totally run-down. The books were dusty and the collection was very poor. Many books were also marked as reference only. Looked like the budget has been severly cut and &#x2F; or the books moved to other libraries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter this library and read books as a visitor. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. The membership cost is less than Rs. 100 per year and you can take 4 books for 2 weeks that you can extend twice or thrice over the phone. For membership, you just need to provide an identity proof and an address proof in Chennai. Aadhar card or driving license should work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find some books that interest you, this might still be worth a membership.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;EXJafR7pJFQ1e4yG9&quot;&gt;735, Anna Salai, Near TVS Bus Stop, Anna Salai, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600002&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Easily accessible from the Thousand Lights Metro station.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No usable online catalog&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;anna-centenary-library&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.annacentenarylibrary.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Anna Centenary Library&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is surely the biggest and the best public library in Chennai. Being the newest, the infrastructure is still very good. It supposedly has 9 floors, but I had time to visit only 3 floors. Surely a great collection of books neatly organized.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter the library and read books. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. Only downer was they refused to provide membership, although the website states the membership categories and fee details. This also being in south Chennai and without metro access, is not very convenient for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;jE5PmEGMsRkQSN2x8&quot;&gt;Gandhi Mandapam Road, Kotturpuram, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600085&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. No metro access&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;117.239.65.6:8001&#x2F;&quot;&gt;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;117.239.65.6:8001&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;connemara-public-library-chennai&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.connemarapubliclibrary.org&#x2F;index.html&quot;&gt;Connemara Public Library Chennai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is likely the oldest public library in Chennai, if not india. There were atleast 4 floors of books with a decent collection that are also available for lending. Overall this looked to be the best option for someone living in north Chennai.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone can visit the library and read books. You just need to sign the register at the entrance. The membership requires you to be a resident of Chennai and also have the form attested by a gazetted officer or a notary public. A bit onerous but looks to be worth it. Books can be extended over the phone for conveninence. Cost should be less than Rs. 200 per year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;tRCR7fjs9ELcT9Yu8&quot;&gt;Pantheon Road, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600008&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Around 2 kms from Egmore metro station.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No usable online catalog&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;american-center-chennai&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;in.usembassy.gov&#x2F;education-culture&#x2F;american-spaces&#x2F;american-space-chennai&#x2F;&quot;&gt;American Center Chennai&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the smallest library that I had visited and the books seemed to be only from US publishers. The collection looked to be irrelevant for someone in India. It would have been redeemed if there were more classics and best sellers from the US, but all the books and magazines seemed to be dated and obscure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone is allowed to enter the library and read books. You need to bring a valid, original photo ID like a driving license, that should be submitted at the security check along with your mobile phone. The membership is very affordable, at Rs 400 per year. Might be worth to consult the online catalog and join for very specific books that might be available only there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;QTbbKc2xvRyFvoS37&quot;&gt;Next to Anna Flyover, Gopalapuram, Chennai, Tamil Nadu 600086&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Around 1.5 kms from Thousand Lights metro station. Enterance is through the gate on the Catherdral road side.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Catalog&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;americanspacesindia.on.worldcat.org&#x2F;discovery&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;americanspacesindia.on.worldcat.org&#x2F;discovery&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Glass bottles</title>
		<published>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/glass-bottles/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/glass-bottles/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wanted a set of glass water bottles which I could use to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.m.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Solar_water_disinfection&quot;&gt;disinfect water, through solar radiation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I obviously did not want to use plastic bottles as they degrade on exposure to the sun and also leech harmful chemicals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched on Amazon and liked this simple one litre &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.amazon.in&#x2F;gp&#x2F;product&#x2F;B07X97R325&quot;&gt;milk bottle model&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which cost Rs. 165 per bottle. This looked way expensive for my liking and I decided to checkout prices from wholesale stores around Parry&#x27;s corner.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nainiappa Naicken street is the street for pharmaceuticals, perfumes and chemicals. It also had a few glass bottle stores and I was able to locate a similar 1 litre milk bottle. I ended up buying an entire box containing 20 nos. for Rs. 800. That comes to around Rs. 40 per bottle. This is way cheap, but transport cost is what would now tip the balance. Fortunately, I was able to use the metro and share-auto to transport the box which was slightly smaller than a checkin luggage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I probably have a life&#x27;s supply of milk bottles :-)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Hello earthworm</title>
		<published>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-earthworm/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-earthworm/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like most of us, I have known from my childhood that, earthworms are one of the best friends of farmers, but after starting hands on farming, I have been able to watch and study them in close quarters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that surprised me was, I had quite a lot of earthworms (probably around 15 to 20 per square feet) for the apparently poor soil, infested with what is locally known as Arugampul (Cyanodon Dactylon or Bermuda Grass).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area was being over grazed by the locals as a pasture for their cows and goats and was highly compacted. In local parlance it is known as Karambu. The only plant life that was there was Bermuda grass. This seemed like the poorest state a land can be in, with whatever that grew, immedately being plundered by voracious cows and goats.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I dig an area of the grass, I still see earthworms nestled in the root and stolon mat of the Bermuda grass. It seems like there is a symbiotic relationship between them and the grass supplies some highly valued food like sugars that the earthworms like. Or it could just be that, below the top few inches where the grass roots and stolons are present, the soil is highly compacted and the earthworms are simply not able to burrow down and move.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the November-December rain season of 2023, I had a crop of horse gram which unfortunaetely died due to water stagnation and some of the beds were completely overrun by Bermuda grass. But I could see better earthworm signs after growing the cover crop. I saw mounds of pelletted soil in some places, which are likely worm castings. These are said to improve the macro structure of the soil and reduce compaction. Earthworm tunnels were everywhere which were totally absent when there was just Bermuda grass. Also, I spotted a few earthworm nests with around 10 to 15 eggs or cocoons.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these seem like good signs and I hope to have better crop in January because of the earthworms&#x27; work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video which shows how earthworms turn plant waste to good soil.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;2Pa1FwmKZcQ?si=F6IQkiaPTJ8wBDWc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Fastag chargebacks</title>
		<published>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-12-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/chargebacks-on-fastag/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/chargebacks-on-fastag/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have got a couple of chargebacks for less than Rs. 200 on my ICICI Fastag account,
in the past few years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first one I totally panicked and raised a ticket
on the online portal which requested for the RC copy to be attached. It took
around a month for the amount to be returned back to my account.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time in Nov 2023, I got another chargeback, but I missed to raise
a ticket immediately. After a few weeks I got a message that my complaint on the
chargeback has been raised. I was perplexed and logged into my account to
look for any tickets that have been raised. And there it was, a ticket
raised in my account, with the RC copy being a screen shot of a Bihar
Transport department website, which allows to pull up RC details with
vehicle number.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if these are genuine faults in the system, but in any case,
I think allowing the company running the toll booth to both raise a
chargeback request and also automatically raising a ticket to dispute the
chargeback, is a process that can be easily abused. Since it takes more than
a month for the dispute to be resolved and money credited back to the
Fastag account, it can be used as operating cash by someone in the system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My guess is, this is likely the toll operators who are doing this. With a
trickle of chargebacks and resolutions after a month, this can be made
to look like genuine faults, but they benefit with a huge cash flow.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably someone needs to file an RTI requesting for the details and also
if there are any penalties levied on the toll provider for incorrect 
chargebacks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching on the Internet, I found &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.team-bhp.com&#x2F;forum&#x2F;street-experiences&#x2F;210138-raise-dispute-trip-new-trick-toll-plazas-cheat-fastag-users.html&quot;&gt;this thread on team-bhp.com&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
dating back to 2019 raising similar concerns. And another &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.moneylife.in&#x2F;article&#x2F;fastag-wrong-deductions-why-complaints-are-not-getting-resolved-sooner&#x2F;63149.html&quot;&gt;long wieldy article
on
moneylife.in&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
giving some data on chargebacks, but nothing that suggests a proper
resolution for this issue.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Datastructures on Hypercore - Queue</title>
		<published>2023-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/datastructures-on-hypercore-queue/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/datastructures-on-hypercore-queue/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; we saw how we can
implement a stack on a hypercore. In this post I explore how to implement a queue
which turned out to be in some ways, more complex than a stack and also simpler.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;take-1&quot;&gt;Take 1&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enqueue and dequeue&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enqeue adds a new element to the back of the queue which we can do by appending
a new block to the hypercore.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To perform a dequeue we need to find the front of
the queue, which is the first block, before we have done any dequeue operation.
But the front keeps increasing
as we perform more dequeues. So to find the front in O(1) time, we add a pointer
to it along with the new element during the append.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To record the new position during dequeue, we append a special block
with just the pointer to the front. Do distinguish the dequeue block, we show
X where the element used to be for an enqueue block.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the hypercore state after 2 enqueues and a dequeue below.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-queue&#x2F;hypercore-queue-1-3.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Queue on Hypercore - Take 1 - Step 3&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Series of dequeues&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system looks good till now, but is still not O(1) for the dequeue operation as
the blocks recording the dequeue states need to be skipped to find the new front.
This can be seen below where in step 7, when we do the dequeue operation, we need to 
skip blocks 5 and 6 before we find the new front, which is 7, and record it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-queue&#x2F;hypercore-queue-1-long-dequeue.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Queue on Hypercore - Take 1 - Long series of deqeues&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;take-2&quot;&gt;Take 2&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple solution for avoiding the clutter of the front pointers is to store it in
a different hypercore than where the elements of the queue is stored.
This is shown below&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-queue&#x2F;hypercore-queue-2-3.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Queue on Hypercore - Take 2&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We update the front of the hypercoreo only in case of a dequeue operation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that is simple!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;code&quot;&gt;Code&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;experiment-hypercore&#x2F;tree&#x2F;main&#x2F;queue-1.js&quot;&gt;Take #1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;experiment-hypercore&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;queue-2.js&quot;&gt;Take #2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Datastructures on Hypercore - Stack</title>
		<published>2023-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/datastructures-on-hypercore-stack/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/datastructures-on-hypercore-stack/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;docs.holepunch.to&#x2F;building-blocks&#x2F;hypercore&quot;&gt;Hypercore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a secure,
distributed append-only log which I have been following since the days of
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dat-ecosystem.org&#x2F;timeline.html&quot;&gt;Dat&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently exploring the datastrcutures that can be implemented over
Hypercore and came up with a few. I will be exploring them in a series of
posts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we will see the representation of a stack with diagrams
representing the state after each step of a series of operations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rectangle represents a block in the Hypercore. The number above it
represents the block number. Hypercore allows blocks to be only added.
So the block number increases monotonically. Also, there is no way to
remove a block. So You will see the total Hypercore size increases as
we progress.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial state is an empty Hypercore which represents an empty stack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On pushing an element into the stack, we ad a new block with the element
added.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-1.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 1 - Push A&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we push another.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-2.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 2 - Push B&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we want to pop the top element. Till now, the top element of the stack
has been the the last block in the Hypercore, but now need to change the
top of the stack. We do this by writing the block number of the top
element as a new block.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-3.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 3 - Pop&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now a block had only the contents of the stack. Now we have an
additional data type that a block can hold which is the block number
of the top element or a pointer to the top. So you might need a type
field as the first byte of the block in your implementation, but we
skip it for simplicity as our block contents are always an alphabet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the block number 2 is shown in gray as any further operations will
never access block number 2. This enables sparse download of the Hypercore
for an new comer or garbage collection of unused blocks for an existing
user.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 4&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we push a new element C. We once again do this by appending a new
block with the element.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-4.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 4 - Push C&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 5&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we want to pop an element from the stack. Since the last block
contains the element directly and is not a pointer we directly read
the value of the top. Now we need to append a block to the Hypercore
with the block number of the previous element in the stack. We do this
by looking at the previous block and if it is an element, we write its
block number as the new top. If instead it is a pointer we write that
as the new top. In this case, we write the pointer value 1.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-5.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 5 - Pop&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 6&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now a final pop to empty the stack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-6.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 6 - Pop&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We read the element A using the top pointer in the last block. Since
there is no previous block, we write the value 0 as the pointer to the
top by appending a new block. You will see that, now the beginning
part of the Hypercore never needs to be downloaded by new users
who are interested only in the latest state.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 7&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we will see how the stack looks with a new element inserted after
the stack has been emptied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13.github.io&#x2F;blog&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-stack&#x2F;hypercore-stack-7.excalidraw.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stack on Hypercore - Step 7 - Pop&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this figure is now self explanatory. You can find the code I
have used at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;experiment-hypercore&#x2F;tree&#x2F;main&#x2F;stack.js&quot;&gt;experiment-hypercore&#x2F;stack.js&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;datastructures-on-hypercore-queue&quot;&gt;next post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, I explore
how we can implement a queue on a hypercore.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Search for Visual Studio Code alternative</title>
		<published>2023-09-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-09-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-vscode-alternative/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-vscode-alternative/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was looking for an alternative to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;code.visualstudio.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
for light editing needs alongside of Android Studio. With Visual Studio Code eating up 360 MB
of RAM when loaded, I can get close to having my entire 8 GB RAM used up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a round of eliminating the alternatives that came up in a Google search, I narrowed
down on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;kate-editor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Kate&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which is the text editor by the venerable KDE
project. It met all my requirements viz. Vim mode, and inbuilt Git support and occupied
just 86 MB of RAM when running.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The also-rans where, &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lighttable.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Lightable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with 109 MB of RAM usage, but without
inbuilt Git support and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.jetbrains.com&#x2F;fleet&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Fleet&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, with 895 MB of RAM usage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Check status of income tax refund</title>
		<published>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/income-tax-refund/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/income-tax-refund/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not sure if this is obscure, but I had to google to find out this page which
gives the status of income tax refund for each assessment year:
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tin.tin.nsdl.com&#x2F;oltas&#x2F;refund-status-pan.html&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tin.tin.nsdl.com&#x2F;oltas&#x2F;refund-status-pan.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Visualizing historical rainfall</title>
		<published>2023-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the limited water capacity in my well, I have to depend mostly on rainfall
for growing crops in my farm. Farmers have a rich traditional knowledge about
the rainfall patterns, but I am very new to following the weather patterns and
wanted to improve my intution. To start with I wanted to visualize the
historical daily rainfall over a few decades and internalize the seasonal
rainfall pattern over my farm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began with searching for a good visualization scheme for seasonal variations
and Spiral plots seemed to be a good option. I mucked around with installing and
trying to use R, but it seemed to require a bit more of initial time investment
to learn it proper before I could understand what I was doing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is written by
the authors of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;d3js.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;D3.js&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I already knew about D3.js as a
good framework and decided to do my visualization with Observable. With a quick
signup using my Google account I was able to play around using the large number
of examples. I also found a spiral heatmap visualization notebook that I was
able to clone and adapt to presenting my data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the result of the visualization showing rainfall over Tindivanam from
January 2000 to February 2023. Rainfall data was taken from
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open-meteo.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;docs&#x2F;historical-weather-api#latitude=12.23&amp;amp;longitude=79.66&amp;amp;start_date=2000-01-01&amp;amp;end_date=2023-02-28&amp;amp;daily=precipitation_sum&amp;amp;timezone=auto&quot;&gt;Open-Meteo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
  src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;f650972998319078?cells=chart&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, I have created &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;visualizing-historical-rainfall-2&quot;&gt;another take on this visualization&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; using the Observable Framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;edits&quot;&gt;Edits&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2023-12-07: Updated rainfall data up to Dec 2023&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2023-04-17: Shortened the title of this post&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Climate Spiral</title>
		<published>2023-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/climate-spiral/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/climate-spiral/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was searching for a nice way to visualize historical rainfall data in my farm and stumbled upon this scary visualization from NASA:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;jWoCXLuTIkI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Search for Mucuna</title>
		<published>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-mucuna/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-mucuna/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I first came across Mucuna, last year, as Black Velvette Bean during the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;solitude.farm&#x2F;farm&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Saturday Farm Tour&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at Solitude Farm, Auroville.
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;krishnamckenzie.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Krishna McKenzie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; explained its benefits for
controlling Parkinsons disease etc. in his inimitable style, but it went way
over my head at that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my search for cover crops for my no-till farming experiments, I came across this
excellent blog called &lt;a href=&quot;farming-experiments.blogspot.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;My Experiments with
Farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
where Nandakumar talks about using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;farming-experiments.blogspot.com&#x2F;2014&#x2F;09&#x2F;invasive-cover-crops-pueraria-javanica.html&quot;&gt;Mucuna as a cover
crop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Interestingly Krishna McKenzie too has a video where he uses Mucuna as a cover
crop which he cuts and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=y0xmEDq3NIs&quot;&gt;mulches over rice
seeds&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Access Agriculture, is
another website that I trust, which also exudes the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.accessagriculture.org&#x2F;reviving-soils-mucuna&quot;&gt;benefits of
Mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so many good things that I heard, I decided to try it in my farm and was
looking for a supplier. I initially contacted &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.indiamart.com&#x2F;vinarghya-pharmaceuticals&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Vinayaga
Pharmaceuticals&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, through
IndiaMART, but they were quoting Rs. 220 per kg + Rs 80 for courier. I also
found a neighbouring natural farmer, but he was quoting Rs. 400 per kg.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally ordered it from the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;seed.iihr.res.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ICAR - IIHR Seed
Portal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for Rs. 120 per kg with an additional postal
and packaging charges of Rs. 118. This was in January 2023. The variety was
marked as ARKA Dhanwantri.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Access raw.githubusercontent.com files in India</title>
		<published>2023-01-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2023-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/access-raw-githubusercontent/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/access-raw-githubusercontent/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As of January 2023, raw.githubusercontent.com domain is blocked by Jio and
possibly other ISPs in India. This likely is due to a wise government or court
order. There is a substantial &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=34231553&quot;&gt;Hacker News
thread&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; discussing this issue,
but the situation has been the same now, for more than a
couple of months.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The block seems to be at the DNS level and I had sucess with using
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;developers.google.com&#x2F;speed&#x2F;public-dns&quot;&gt;Google&#x27;s Public DNS&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; server.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To change the DNS server I updated the &lt;em&gt;DNS servers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; setting in the
Jio broadband router under &lt;em&gt;Network &amp;gt; LAN &amp;gt; DNS servers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. Change the option to
select &lt;em&gt;Use Below&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and enter Google&#x27;s primary and secondary DNS servers viz.
&lt;em&gt;8.8.8.8&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;8.8.4.4.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;DNS Servers&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; setting seems to get reset to
&lt;em&gt;Use DNS Proxy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, every time I reboot the router. So, finally I had to set the
custom DNS directly on my PC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my Redmi phone, there is no way to set a custom DNS as the setting has been
removed by Xiaomi. The easiest way to overcome this was to use
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;play.google.com&#x2F;store&#x2F;apps&#x2F;details?id=com.cloudflare.onedotonedotonedotone&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=US&quot;&gt;1.1.1.1 + Warp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
from Cloudflare. This provides a VPN configuration that uses Cloudflare&#x27;s
free DNS resolver at 1.1.1.1.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the DNS server change didn&#x27;t seem to work on my desktop. In this case, I got
unblocked by using the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.torproject.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Tor Browser&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This doesn&#x27;t
help with other apps that make a request to &lt;em&gt;raw.githubusercontent.com&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I ran into
this problem again when installing &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;doomemacs&#x2F;doomemacs&quot;&gt;Doom Emacs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
which unfortunately needed to download some files from the cursed github domain.
After some Googling, I ended up using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;haad&#x2F;proxychains&quot;&gt;ProxyChains&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to make the Doom Emacs install command to use the local tor connection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;bash&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#2b303b;color:#c0c5ce;&quot; class=&quot;language-bash &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; service tor start
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; apt install proxychains
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#bf616a;&quot;&gt;proxychains ~&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#x2F;.config&#x2F;emacs&#x2F;bin&#x2F;doom install
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yay! I don&#x27;t need to buy a VPN now, just because I cheaped out choosing Jio.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; As of 5 October, 2023, I am still unable to access content from raw.githubusercontent.com
when using Jio Broadband unless I use one of the above techniques.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Install Rust for all users</title>
		<published>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/install-rust-for-all-users/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/install-rust-for-all-users/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I wanted a single rust compiler to be installed system wide, but the
default result of using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;rustup.rs&#x2F;&quot;&gt;rustup&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is, it is installed
locally in the current user&#x27;s home directory.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a bit of searching on the Internet and some dead ends, I stumbled on
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;rust-lang&#x2F;rustup&#x2F;issues&#x2F;1085&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;rust-lang&#x2F;rustup&#x2F;issues&#x2F;1085&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which seems to be mostly working.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting thing I learned from the above is that, the script that was
suggested for &#x27;rustc&#x27; can simply be symlinked to other commands like &#x27;cargo&#x27;
and it still works as it uses some
&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;mywiki.wooledge.org&#x2F;BashSheet#Parameter_Operations&quot;&gt;parameter expansion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
magic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also for whatever reason I had to do a &lt;code&gt;sudo rustup component add rust-src&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;
to make rust-analyzer work with Visual Studio Code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Hello world</title>
		<published>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2022-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-world/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-world/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello world!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
