<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>My Experiments - farming</title>
	<subtitle>My Blog and Projects</subtitle>
	<link href="https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/farming/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://arunkd13.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/farming/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Andhra Pradesh Community managed Natural Farming</title>
		<published>2024-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/apcnf/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/apcnf/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;apcnf.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Andhra Pradesh Community managed Natural Farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or
APCNF project is the only active government run natural farming program I could find in
India. They have a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;@APZBNF&quot;&gt;Youtube channel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that has a
large number of videos showing the principles and practices that are recommended
to farmers, but most of them are in Telugu. Even though I follow a bit of
it, I was not able to get the full details of specific procedures they recommend
to the farmers. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;nfcoalition.in&#x2F;people&#x2F;t-vijay-kumar&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Vijay Kumar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, who
heads the APCNF organization, has promised in one of the webinars held recently, that,
the content will soon be translated to
English for the benefit of people from the other states of India. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most valuable finds from the APCNF channel was the lecture by Walter
Jehne, an Australian microbiologist and cliamtologist, on &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=GaXR3zLIM1U&quot;&gt;Regenerative
Agriculture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. His theory is that the
natural systems like soil and forests have kept the climate in a steady state
through millions of years through the natural process of rainfall and
transpiration. The destruction of forests and soil to acquire land for modern
industrial scale agriculture has had more impact on global temperatures than
increase in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;sub&gt;. By restoring these systems, we can bring down global
temeperatures. Also restoring the soil goes a longer way in capturing rainfall
than building dams and other irrigation projects. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APCNF itself uses these theories and applies them to the farming practices
followed by actual farmers which is were the real test lies. For a short
overview on APCNF, I would recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;afsafrica.org&#x2F;wp-content&#x2F;uploads&#x2F;2022&#x2F;10&#x2F;natural-farming-guide-digital-lr.pdf&quot;&gt;this booklet called Taking Agroecology to
Scale&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
by an organisation called Alliance for Food Sovereignty in Africa (AFSA), which
had studied APCNF with the goal of applying the learnings in Africa.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own journey in farming has been influenced till now by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Masanobu_Fukuoka&quot;&gt;Masanobu
Fukuoka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;G._Nammalvar&quot;&gt;Nammazhvar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;resources&#x2F;a045e67c-53fa-4ff9-be2a-f24707d41b58&quot;&gt;Roland
Bunch&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and my own experience battling the &lt;em&gt;arugampul&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (Cynodon dactylon) ridden
compacted soil for the past 1.5 years (since January 2023).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, I have collected my thoughts on the APCNF principles and how I can
integrate them into my own practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;365 days of ground cover&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that having something growing throughout the year maximizes the
capture of solar energy and adds more biomass to the soil. But this is also
important for keeping the soil life alive and ready for the next crop. Also, soil with
growing plants capture more of the rain water than barren soil.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main challenge in my land is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;supplying the required soil
moisture&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for
growing crops througout the year. The well on my farm has sufficient water for
irrigation only during January to March, which is after the heavy North East
monsoon during the months from October to December. There are a few scattered
showers during the months of April and May, but they are not sufficient to
establish any new crop. The South West monsoon which starts in June, brings
intermittent rainfall, but I haven&#x27;t been able to retain enough moisture for a
successful crop in 2023 without additional irrigation. During the NE monsoon
season of 2023, I had the reverse
problem of water stagnation on my bunded field. I had missed to promptly drain
the fields after the bouts of heavy rains.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address these,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to identify crops that are suitable for each of these
seasons. A crop that is already established during during January and February
can withstand the hot and dry months of March to May. So intercropping a short
duration crop and a longer duration crop could be a solution.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sequence of crops is also important. For example, it is better to
grow a grain or food crop after &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;search-for-mucuna&quot;&gt;mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as it leaves the
field rich with nitrogen and reduced weed growth. Also, I am hoping that as the
soil structure improves, it can percolate more of the rain water allowing plant
growth during the dry spells.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also need to find an alternative to mucuna which
requires lesser water, as I will not have sufficient water for irrigation if I
increase the land under cultivation. Canavalia (&lt;em&gt;thamattai avarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil), is
supposed to be more drought tolerant than mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diverse crops including trees&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi cropping i.e. growing more than one crop in the same field is a big part
of APCNF&#x27;s recommendation. This is not just a legume and a grain intercopped,
but 8 to 12 species grown together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is surely a challenge to grow so many varied crops in the same field close
together, even though I do everything with just manual labour. Harvesting
becomes more complex and I have to go through multiple passes, picking each of
the crop separately. Some crops like
mucuna cannot be grown together with other crops as they grow aggresively and
bury other plants below their lush growth, if there is sufficient water for them
to grow. Similarly, I have seen &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;horse-gram&quot;&gt;Horsegram&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; also smother other
plants.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big part of this recommendation is growing trees along with field crops.
The trees supposedly provide shade and reduce evaporation of moisture
from the top layers of the soil. This would be useful especially during
the months from March to May when it might not be possible to have field crops
growing due to lack of water, whereas the trees with deeper roots would continue
to be growing. The trees can be pruned before establishing the next crop in June
or July to provide adequete sunshine for the field crop. The leaves and small
branches from the pruned trees can be used as mulch. This technique is also
called Alley cropping i.e. growing field crops between hedged rows of trees and is a
well established practice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on this,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to determine compatibility matrix of each crop with the others.
From this, I need to create guilds of crops that can be grown together.
Combining this with the seasonal elements is going to be interesting.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to find the perennial trees and long duration plants that can be
grown on the hedge rows. I think it might be difficult to grow fruit trees in this manner as the field
crop is going to get the higher priority in terms of when the tree will be
pruned. Leguminous trees like &lt;em&gt;Agathi&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Sesbania_grandiflora&quot;&gt;Sesbania
grandiflora&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Gliricidia&quot;&gt;Gliricidia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are a good option.
I also plan to expriment with trees that are naturally dispersed in my field like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Azadirachta_indica&quot;&gt;Neem tree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pencil Maram&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
(&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Acacia_auriculiformis&quot;&gt;Acacia auriculiformis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Borassus_flabellifer&quot;&gt;Palm tree&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Timber
trees like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Teak&quot;&gt;Teak&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; are also be a good
option.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another interesting technique I intend to follow is called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.echocommunity.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;resources&#x2F;bb74e905-3feb-4c87-9638-1b4f028cd778&quot;&gt;Farmer Managed
Natural
Regeneration&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
This is the technique where the farmer nurtures and grows the tree saplings
that naturally popup every year all over the field and were sown by birds,
squirrels and other animals. What a joy it is, to work with nature! 
If left to nature, it is very much capable of turning the land into
robust forest in a decade, but we then lose our ability to grow
field crops. So we still need to decide
which saplings and how many, we nurture and which ones we destroy. This
technique doesn&#x27;t create neat rows of trees like in alley cropping, but
the trees end up disperesed all over the field. Nevertheless, the utility
should still be the same with no major disadvantages.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No&#x2F;low till&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the key principles of Fukuoka and the primary technique which
pulled me into farming. I have clearly seen, from my experience, how tilling destroys
&lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;hello-earthworm&quot;&gt;the soil structure that nature had tirelessly built&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But starting from a compacted soil, it is very difficult to grow the first few
years of crop. Usually it is recommended to start with a well tilled field
without grass or weeds and follow no till from the second year onwards. For some
reason, I am not inclined to do it. Maybe, I want to prove the power of nature in restoring even a
compacted degraded soil without fossil fuel inputs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only disturbance I am doing is to dig a 1 feet wide trench every 1.5 meters
which I use for irrigation and also as a drainage mechanism during
rains. I use the soil from the trenches to form the tall bunds which demarcate
the fields and retain the water. The trenches can also be used to hold excess biomass
after laying out as mulch on the beds. The trenches are dug perpendicular to the
slope of the land and slows down the flow of water and helps in percolation.
It also provides a path to walk within the field for inspection
and harvesting. In effect the field looks like parallel rows of raised beds, which
makes the job of sowing a lot more cumbersome than broadcasting on flat
rectangular field.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not been able to perform a true Fukuoka style broadcast sowing using
seed balls. I am forced to hoe down the grass atleast an inch or two after I
broadcast, without which the seeds do not have sufficient contact with the
soil and are likely to be eaten away. Also hoeing kills the weeds and
without which there is too much competition for the crop to get established.
This is a back breaking work and is not scalable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been fascinated by Krishna McKenzie&#x27;s technique of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=y0xmEDq3NIs&quot;&gt;sowing rice
over a cover crop of mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Mucuna forms a dense layer of vegetation which suppresses grass and other
weeds and the crop grown after, is able to establish quickly without much
competition. The effort in preparing the soil by hoeing and drilling the seeds is greatly reduced.
We simply broadcast the seeds over the growing mucuna plants and then we enter the field to
cut the vines and shake it to ensure the seeds reach the soil and lay the cut vines over it. There is
sufficient disturbance when pulling at the vines and stepping on the soil, to lightly bury
the seeds. The leaf litter and vines also cover the seeds to hide them
from birds and also decay quickly to form an additional layer of rich soil over the seeds.
Also the crop gets to use the nitrogen fixed by mucuna,
in addition to the nitrogen from the decaying green leaves.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have already tried this over one season, but had to still hoe to
remove the weeds that refused to be suppressed. I was also not confident that the
seeds would get buried enough to have proper germination. I think over the
years, the weed pressure should reduce so that I can skip the hoeing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to monitor the effort needed to sow on these raised beds vs a flat
field. There are tradeoffs between sowing effort and the better irrigation
between the two.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to perfect the technique of sowing over a cover crop of mucuna as a scalable
mechanism for planting and weed control. I should try this out with other
grains like bajra and ragi and also experiment with other cover crops like
canavalia, instead of mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to really evaluate if making seed pellets is worth the effort
compared to sowing over mucuna. This will allow me to have two continous crops
instead of having to reserve one crop for mucuna.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrate animals into farming&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Animals require more active care and constant human presence. I want to
establish a farming practice where I would only be present on the farm for a few
days of the week. If I had farm animals, I would have to employ someone who
needs to stay with the animals 24&#x2F;7. This complicates the whole model. This
might be something I might consider later, but I decided to avoid using animals
for now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still get dung from cows that the villagers graze on the uncultivated
parts of my land and also the adjacent land. The villagers do collect the manure
dropped and take it with them to their own fields, but, I have been able to
collect some for myself and have experimented with making crude &lt;em&gt;Jeevamurtham&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;
that I add to the irrigation water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manavari Velanmai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a traditional agriculture practice, where the farmer tills
the soil and sows the seeds before the rain and comes back to the field only to
harvest. So, there are precedences for avoiding constant presence in the farm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do fancy growing hens, but it needs to wait until I have the food grain
business going sustainably.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use of bio stimulants&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;APCNF recommends adding solid and liquid bio-stimulants made from manure and
plant carbohydrates and also making Fukuoka style &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=X0cxJ9shbcI&quot;&gt;seed
pellets&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; treated with the same.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, I have made a bit of crude Jeevamrutham, but could not see visible impact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting good quantity of clay for making the pellets has been a challenge. I have made small
quantities of clay by &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=ca20JkKFAcE&quot;&gt;dissolving the soil from my farm in water and letting the
water drip out of the solution through something like a cheese
cloth&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. But could not find an easy
way to grind the dried clay blocks to a powder to use in the pelletization
process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this forward,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to find a good way
to grind the processed dry clay and expriment with pelletization, atleast on a
small scale.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to evaluate the effectiveness of these bio stimulants in a more
appropriate scenario. I also need to experiment using the palm fruit as a free 
sugar source for making these bio stimulants.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crop residue and mulch&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This matches Fukuoka&#x27;s method of leaving the crop residue as a mulch over the
broadcasted seeds. I have clearly noticed the soil below the mulch retain
moisture better than the bare soil. This is also a key part of the Green Manure
Cover Crop practice advocated by Roland Bunch.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximizing the organic matter production is a key requirement for this. I am
using cover crops like mucuna and sunn hemp purely for organic matter
production, although I don&#x27;t have any other uses for them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to evaluate more dual purpose crops, which produce food in
addition to large amount of bio mass. Some crops to try, include, Canavalia
(&lt;em&gt;thamattai avarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil) which looks to be bit more palatable than
mucuna and pigeon pea (&lt;em&gt;tuvarai&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in Tamil) which is similar to sunn hemp in
growing in poor soil and withstanding drought.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Farmer&#x27;s own seed or local seeds&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is very import to make farming self reliant without any external input,
but, having sufficient quantity of seed stock of the right variety needed for
the season is difficult. Selling seeds on a small scale is made more difficult
by a number of laws that purport to maintain seed
quality. So the farmer needs to maintain their own robust seed bank. Vialbility
also reduces when stored for multiple years, along with insects
attacking the seeds. So the seeds need to be regularly replaced with fresh
seeds from growing crops.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have started out with buying most of my seeds from the local agricultural
supply stores around Tindivanam. These are likely commercial varieties that
might be bred to take advantage of chemical inputs. I haven&#x27;t tried
heirloom seeds yet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been able to replenish my seed bank with my own seeds for mucuna and sunn hemp, but doing it for the
food crops like, green gram, cow pea etc. has been difficult as I end up storing
the seeds incorrectly leading to insect atack.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need a more disciplined storage method and a way to track their age.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I need to study the characterstics of different varities of the same crop
to select seeds suited for my climate, soil and the style of natural farming
that I perform.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pest &amp;amp; disease management through botanical ingredients&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not faced any significant crop loss due to pest attack, likely because,
the yield is already low due to other reasons. Also, it is said that, the pests
attack only weak crops and when external
fertilizers, either manure or artificial, is added, weak crops crowd out the
field over the hardy ones and later end up getting attacked by pests. This leads
to significant crop loss compared to just letting these weak crops die early and
letting the hardy crops provide a lower yield.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I would be able to find right balance between the two.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strict NO to chemical inputs&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this is the easist principle to follow if you aren&#x27;t constrained by
needing high yields. In addition to saving money, chemicals like Glyphosate
which is used as a weedicide, pose a risk to human health. Here I prefer using
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Precautionary_principle&quot;&gt;precautionary
principle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of not using a
technique that has a risk of damaging
human health than waiting for it to be proven.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have learnt a lot from studying APCNF. Using it as a framework for evaluating my
current practice has given me a confidence that I am going in the right path and
given me a number of new ideas that I can try out and improve on. I now have a better
picture of what my end goal looks like in my journey to grow food without using
fossil fuels.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>@sunson</title>
		<published>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/sunson/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right from my school days when I started using the Internet, I had been
following people on the Internet, from whom I have continously learnt and shaped my
understanding of the world. Although it might sound a bit kitsch, I would compare this to the
relationship between &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Ekalavya&quot;&gt;Ekalavya and
Dronacharya&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but the comparison breaks
down when I gratefully recollect how much more I have received from my gurus than
what Ekalavya received from Dronacharya. And have I been as worthy a student as
Ekalavya? I don&#x27;t think so.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of these exemplary gurus and closest to my heart has been Suraj Kumar. I
remember, the first time I saw him was around 1998, in one of the ILUGC (Indian Linux User&#x27;s
Group - Chennai) meetings held regularly in the IIT Madras campus. He was the same age as
me, but vastly more knowledgeable and driven. I was this reticent Linux newbie
and was at
awe with the MoM&#x27;s he wrote after
each meeting - every detail captured in his pleasant style with a unique sense
of humour.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued to follow his posts as &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;@sunson on Live
Journal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;sunsonian&quot;&gt;@sunsonian on
Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The later half of the 2000s were the
heydays of Web 2.0 and
there were increasingly more options for staying connected and learning from my
gurus.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I internalized a number of life changing concepts like &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Peak_oil&quot;&gt;Peak
oil&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Emergence&quot;&gt;Emergence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; through his writings and
the links he posted on the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Delicious_(website)&quot;&gt;Delicious bookmarking
website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. He introduced me to
other communities like &lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;theoildrum.com&#x2F;special&#x2F;archives&quot;&gt;The Oil Drum&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
which opened their own wide worlds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I was already an atheist, @sunson&#x27;s explorations and thoughts were much
deeper. He introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Richard_Dawkins&quot;&gt;Richard
Dawkins&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and I devoured his
books, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_Selfish_Gene&quot;&gt;The Selfish Gene&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;The_God_Delusion&quot;&gt;The God Delusion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest impact he had on me must be his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.flickr.com&#x2F;photos&#x2F;sunson&#x2F;albums&#x2F;72157626205527503&quot;&gt;efforts at natural
farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I
eagerly followed his journey as he introduced me to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Masanobu_Fukuoka&quot;&gt;Masanobu
Fukuoka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s writings and
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;G._Nammalvar&quot;&gt;Nammalvar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&#x27;s work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This had a great impact on my own journey into natural farming that I
started in January 2022.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks like everything ends where it starts and I learn &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.freelists.org&#x2F;post&#x2F;ilugc&#x2F;ILUGC-Trichy,6&quot;&gt;from this post on the ILUGC mailing
list&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that @sunson is no longer
with us. In this ephemeral digital
age, I am thankful that the Internet Archive&#x27;s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Wayback_Machine&quot;&gt;Wayback
Machine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has his &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;web.archive.org&#x2F;web&#x2F;20231204190058&#x2F;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sunson.livejournal.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Live Journal
blog
archived&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
although his delicious bookmarks and his personal website are lost. The Twitter
feed anf Flickr photos hang on a noose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope his writings survive the bitrot and continue to educate and
inspire more of us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Visualizing historical rainfall - Part 2</title>
		<published>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall-2/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall-2/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2023, I made a &lt;a href=&quot;visualizing-historical-rainfall.md&quot;&gt;visualization of the historical rainfall over my farm&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to help me improve my farming practice. This was made using the the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; tool.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in 2024, Observable folks released the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;framework&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable Framework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
which is a Javascript framework that can be used to create standalone
visualizations and built into a static website. This sounded exciting and I decided to take another
stab at rainfall visualization using this framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see it embedded below.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;950&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also access the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arunkd13-public.observablehq.cloud&#x2F;climate&#x2F;&quot;&gt;standalone website&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;arunkd13&#x2F;climate-dash&quot;&gt;source code&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is available on Github.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Water on soil</title>
		<published>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/water-on-soil/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/water-on-soil/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The effectiveness of both rainfall and irrigation depend on the soil type, structure and the natural slope of the land. This is even more important for growing crops only with rain water. So having good intutive understanding of the action of water on soil is important for successful farming.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following video shows live demonstrations of how water flows on different soil types and layers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;ego2FkuQwxc?si=fl8l_LETyKWh4vNo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video helped me reason the effectivenss of a no-till agriculture. Following are the thoughts I had when I watched this video:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aggregated soil, is best for water penetration. Soil that is physically aggregated by plowing gets compacted after a one or two rains or irrgations. It forms a hard crust, which I have seen farmers manually break with a hoe before they irrigate, so that the irrigation is effective. Soil that is aggregated with organic matter, is held together with excrements from the soil life that act like glue and structure is not easily destroyed by water.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregated soil needs to be at the top where rain falls and is not effective if it is buried below a layer of fine powdered or compacted soil. Also the pores and channels made by animals need to be exposed at the top. Disturbing the soil by shallow plouging or even a hoe closes these pores and channels. What aggregated soil that may remain below the plough line is ineffective.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic matter that is buried below the soil does not help water infiltration. Traditionally it resulted in rapid decomposition and release of nutrients, but as with all techniques that help with short term results, you are basically stealing from your future. Organic matter is best left at the top as a mulch where it aids water infiltration, provides natural protection for insects, worms and animals which improve the soil structure. It also shades the soil and provides a better environment for the creatures to thrive. Fertility build up takes more time in this scenario, but is more resilient and increases over time, instead of getting depleted as with ploughing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Hello earthworm</title>
		<published>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-earthworm/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/hello-earthworm/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like most of us, I have known from my childhood that, earthworms are one of the best friends of farmers, but after starting hands on farming, I have been able to watch and study them in close quarters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that surprised me was, I had quite a lot of earthworms (probably around 15 to 20 per square feet) for the apparently poor soil, infested with what is locally known as Arugampul (Cyanodon Dactylon or Bermuda Grass).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area was being over grazed by the locals as a pasture for their cows and goats and was highly compacted. In local parlance it is known as Karambu. The only plant life that was there was Bermuda grass. This seemed like the poorest state a land can be in, with whatever that grew, immedately being plundered by voracious cows and goats.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I dig an area of the grass, I still see earthworms nestled in the root and stolon mat of the Bermuda grass. It seems like there is a symbiotic relationship between them and the grass supplies some highly valued food like sugars that the earthworms like. Or it could just be that, below the top few inches where the grass roots and stolons are present, the soil is highly compacted and the earthworms are simply not able to burrow down and move.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the November-December rain season of 2023, I had a crop of horse gram which unfortunaetely died due to water stagnation and some of the beds were completely overrun by Bermuda grass. But I could see better earthworm signs after growing the cover crop. I saw mounds of pelletted soil in some places, which are likely worm castings. These are said to improve the macro structure of the soil and reduce compaction. Earthworm tunnels were everywhere which were totally absent when there was just Bermuda grass. Also, I spotted a few earthworm nests with around 10 to 15 eggs or cocoons.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these seem like good signs and I hope to have better crop in January because of the earthworms&#x27; work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a video which shows how earthworms turn plant waste to good soil.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;2Pa1FwmKZcQ?si=F6IQkiaPTJ8wBDWc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Visualizing historical rainfall</title>
		<published>2023-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-04-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/visualizing-historical-rainfall/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the limited water capacity in my well, I have to depend mostly on rainfall
for growing crops in my farm. Farmers have a rich traditional knowledge about
the rainfall patterns, but I am very new to following the weather patterns and
wanted to improve my intution. To start with I wanted to visualize the
historical daily rainfall over a few decades and internalize the seasonal
rainfall pattern over my farm.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began with searching for a good visualization scheme for seasonal variations
and Spiral plots seemed to be a good option. I mucked around with installing and
trying to use R, but it seemed to require a bit more of initial time investment
to learn it proper before I could understand what I was doing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Observable&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is written by
the authors of &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;d3js.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;D3.js&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I already knew about D3.js as a
good framework and decided to do my visualization with Observable. With a quick
signup using my Google account I was able to play around using the large number
of examples. I also found a spiral heatmap visualization notebook that I was
able to clone and adapt to presenting my data.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the result of the visualization showing rainfall over Tindivanam from
January 2000 to February 2023. Rainfall data was taken from
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;open-meteo.com&#x2F;en&#x2F;docs&#x2F;historical-weather-api#latitude=12.23&amp;amp;longitude=79.66&amp;amp;start_date=2000-01-01&amp;amp;end_date=2023-02-28&amp;amp;daily=precipitation_sum&amp;amp;timezone=auto&quot;&gt;Open-Meteo&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;800&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
  src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;observablehq.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;f650972998319078?cells=chart&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2024, I have created &lt;a href=&quot;..&#x2F;visualizing-historical-rainfall-2&quot;&gt;another take on this visualization&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; using the Observable Framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;edits&quot;&gt;Edits&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2023-12-07: Updated rainfall data up to Dec 2023&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2023-04-17: Shortened the title of this post&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Search for Mucuna</title>
		<published>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-mucuna/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/search-for-mucuna/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I first came across Mucuna, last year, as Black Velvette Bean during the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;solitude.farm&#x2F;farm&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Saturday Farm Tour&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at Solitude Farm, Auroville.
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;krishnamckenzie.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Krishna McKenzie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; explained its benefits for
controlling Parkinsons disease etc. in his inimitable style, but it went way
over my head at that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my search for cover crops for my no-till farming experiments, I came across this
excellent blog called &lt;a href=&quot;farming-experiments.blogspot.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;My Experiments with
Farming&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
where Nandakumar talks about using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;farming-experiments.blogspot.com&#x2F;2014&#x2F;09&#x2F;invasive-cover-crops-pueraria-javanica.html&quot;&gt;Mucuna as a cover
crop&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.
Interestingly Krishna McKenzie too has a video where he uses Mucuna as a cover
crop which he cuts and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=y0xmEDq3NIs&quot;&gt;mulches over rice
seeds&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Access Agriculture, is
another website that I trust, which also exudes the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.accessagriculture.org&#x2F;reviving-soils-mucuna&quot;&gt;benefits of
Mucuna&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With so many good things that I heard, I decided to try it in my farm and was
looking for a supplier. I initially contacted &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.indiamart.com&#x2F;vinarghya-pharmaceuticals&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Vinayaga
Pharmaceuticals&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, through
IndiaMART, but they were quoting Rs. 220 per kg + Rs 80 for courier. I also
found a neighbouring natural farmer, but he was quoting Rs. 400 per kg.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally ordered it from the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;seed.iihr.res.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ICAR - IIHR Seed
Portal&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for Rs. 120 per kg with an additional postal
and packaging charges of Rs. 118. This was in January 2023. The variety was
marked as ARKA Dhanwantri.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
