<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
	<title>My Experiments - politics</title>
	<subtitle>My Blog and Projects</subtitle>
	<link href="https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/politics/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <link href="https://arunkd13.github.io"/>
	<generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
	<updated>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/tags/politics/atom.xml</id>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>K. P. Park</title>
		<published>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/kp-park/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/kp-park/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I participated in one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Tamil_Nadu_Urban_Habitat_Development_Board&quot;&gt;TNUHDB&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; audits that Arappor Iyakkam does periodically. This was at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;52oTqCWz686iGv8J7&quot;&gt;K. P. Park&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on De Mellows Road in Pulianthope that is also famous for the abysmal plastering and finishing work for which Arappor Iyakkam had previously raised a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=jZjMUoie_ns&quot;&gt;complaint with DVAC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the volunteers had gathered at the meeting point, and we could see the towering buildings painted in bright inviting colors, looking better than I had imagined. We entered the site and went into the nearest block. The more experienced volunteers immediately chose to survey the lifts, since it had become a concern after a person lost his life inside it due to an accident around a year back.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We approached the lift operator who was quite friendly and he told that only one of the lifts was working. The other one had not been funcitoning for the past 3 months. A quick enquiry with other residents waiting for the lift and we got numbers like 1.5 years. The lifts in the next block we visited was in a worse situation. The operator said only one of the two lifts functioned. But when we tried to press the button to summon the lift, he said, &amp;quot;Sir, wait, I will go to the second floor and bring it down. The button doesn&#x27;t work&amp;quot;. Yes, he was telling the truth. The lift works. Only the button doesn&#x27;t work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These towers had something like 10 to 12 floors and lifts were absolutely essential. Only one of the towers we visited had a working generator backup. The other one was supposedly under repair after rats chewed away the wires. This was on a Sunday evening and I can only imagine the chaos during rush hours on a working day.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we came down the stairs from the 10th floor, we saw the other stark problem of K. P. Park. Garbage was strewn all over the stair case. We continued descending, placing each step with caution. Suddenly we stepped on a landing that was unusually clean. Someone wise, had pasted a wall paper with Mother Mary holding Baby Jesus in her hands. A makeshift shrine on the vertical roadways of K. P. Park.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming down we couldn&#x27;t stop noticing garbage that followed us everywhere we looked. The OTS areas were the most affected with more than a dozen rats making a happy meal out of it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking to the residents, we came to know that the conservancy workers clean it every day, but it gets filled very soon by residents in the top floors dropping their daily waste directly out of their windows. There have also been &lt;em&gt;accidents&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; where someone had inadvertently stepped under such a falling bag. The conservancy workers have all been given helmets to safe guard their heads as they go about cleaning the area.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had learnt in the audit pre-brief that many of the TNUHDB tenements had Resident Welfare Associations (RWAs) that ran the maintenance and were also responsible for spending the fund allocated by the Government. At K. P. Park, none of the blocks had one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There also seemed to be vertical segregation happening with the less previlieged people relocated recently from nearby areas like Egmore allocated residences on the top floors. While the people who had been living in the previous settlement that had been demolished to build this highrise, put up in the lower floors. One of the residents put the blame for the garbage squarely on &amp;quot;...those uncivilized people living on the top floors. What can the government do?&amp;quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if mixing less privileged people across all floors would help the situation. But the same forces that end up pushing people dispersed througout the city into this single town within a city, are also likely oprating within this town.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wondered if mixing the less previliged people across all the floors would help the situation. But the same forces that end up pushing people dispersed throughout the city into this single town within a city, are also likely operating within this town.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing people for the better is always a difficult task. More than anti-corruption activists, what this settlement needs are community organizers. Will we be able to fill these shoes?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Seeking action against TANGEDCO and the Adani Group</title>
		<published>2024-12-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2025-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/tangedco-adani-scam/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/tangedco-adani-scam/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Late evening of January 3, 2025, a bit more than 24 hours from the
planned time of protest, Arappor Iyakkam was informed by the Commissioner of
Police, that their request for permission to protest was denied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of the protest, we had to &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=pTiIMpn80Xo&quot;&gt;protest against the rejection of permission
to protest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; within the confines of
the Arappor Iyakkam office.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Arappor Iyakkam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has called for a protest against the
Central and Tamil Nadu State Governments on January 5, 2025 at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;maps.app.goo.gl&#x2F;iBBSm2h2WBVP6gUH9&quot;&gt;Valluvar Kottam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, seeking
action against
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Tamil_Nadu_Generation_and_Distribution_Corporation&quot;&gt;TANGEDCO&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and the Adani Group on the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.occrp.org&#x2F;en&#x2F;investigation&#x2F;new-evidence-bolsters-allegations-adani-group-overcharged-for-coal&quot;&gt;substandard coal purchase
scam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and more.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pbs.twimg.com&#x2F;media&#x2F;GfAULtLaUAA8q2k?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=small&quot; alt=&quot;India is not for sale&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no dearth of allegations of corruption, bribes, scams and fraud against
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Adani_Group&quot;&gt;Adani Group&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;—more than half
their Wikipedia page is dedicated to them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, many people say, this is all an international conspiracy to limit the
growth rate of India&#x27;s GDP and prevent it from becoming a “superpower”. But,
they give the same answer even when we ask why the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.google.com&#x2F;finance&#x2F;quote&#x2F;USD-INR?hl=en&amp;amp;window=MAX&quot;&gt;value of the
INR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; has fallen
by more than 30 %, with respect to the USD, from the day Prime Minister
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Narendra_Modi&quot;&gt;Narendra Modi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; took office in
2014.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Indian_National_Developmental_Inclusive_Alliance&quot;&gt;INDIA
coalition&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
of which the DMK is a part of, is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;economictimes.indiatimes.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;politics-and-nation&#x2F;india-bloc-mps-hold-protest-in-parliament-complex-over-adani-issue-demand-jpc-probe&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;115961485.cms&quot;&gt;demanding a JPC
probe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on the allegations against the Adani Group in the wake of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Indictment_against_Gautam_Adani_et_al.&quot;&gt;indictment
against Gautam Adani et
al.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; in a
US District Court.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Chief Minister &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;M._K._Stalin&quot;&gt;M. K. Stalin&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
who is part of this coalition had also been a vehement opposer of the “corrupt
Adani Group”, but it was before he was elected as CM in 2021. He hasn&#x27;t shown
the same fervour, now that he has the power to prosecute them. Would this
be the same that the Congress and Rahul Gandhi would do if elected to power?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This double faced politics and people&#x27;s helplessness towards it, is very
dangerous. Crony capitalism at a different time, helped the East India Company
take over India. If we intend to retain our hard-earned freedom, we need to be
vigilant against it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus on the TANGEDCO-Adani Coal Scam and the Chief
Minister M. K. Stalin is just a tool in the fight against this bigger problem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February 9, 2018:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; The leader of the opposition Mr. M. K. Stalin, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;stalin-demands-cbi-probe-into-coal-import&#x2F;article22696633.ece&quot;&gt;demanded a CBI
probe&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
on the alleged import of substandard coal by TANGEDCO, benefiting the Adani
Group. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Edappadi_K._Palaniswami&quot;&gt;Edapadi K.
Palaniswami&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; of the AIADMK
was the Chief Minister at that time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;August 6, 2018:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Arappor Iyakkam &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeifgcqe4olo4k5shdgt4bvw27abirnzhwf7w7abxqrzmejcu4u6rra&quot;&gt;submitted a
complaint&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
with the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.dvac.tn.gov.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Department of Vigilance and
Anti-Corruption&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; on this import of substandard coal
and corresponding loss to the exchequer of around ₹6066 crores.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 4, 2019:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Arappor Iyakkam submitted &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeibwjgqfjhhbujvleoasstckkyaxmfzbuxj5zxzbtrbzhwzntlj6ni&quot;&gt;additional
evidence&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
to the DVAC on the lower pricing of the coal purchased by TNPL compared to
TANGEDCO for the same quality.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 2021:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Stalin became the Chief Minister. The once vehement opposer of corruption in TANGEDCO, let the complaints languish with the DVAC.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 31, 2023:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, Arappor Iyakkam reminded him by sending a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;fuchsia-shallow-minnow-246.mypinata.cloud&#x2F;ipfs&#x2F;bafybeihj2qqqhejgp2cefetma67otfmou35sq76ffgycvy5kq7qdqpspkq&quot;&gt;letter &lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
demanding that the DVAC immediately start investigating the complaint and register an FIR against TANGEDCO officials
and the Adani Group.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July 2, 2024:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; It was widely reported that the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;tamil-nadu-probe-launched-into-coal-import-scam-involving-adani-group&#x2F;article68359304.ece&quot;&gt;DVAC has got the nod from the
State
Government&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
and had registered a preliminary enquiry on the allegations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In just a few days on July 9, 2024:&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; Gautam Adani flew down to Chennai on a chartered plane and according to
a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&#x2F;city&#x2F;chennai&#x2F;adani-groups-interest-in-parandur-airport-and-kattupalli-port-creates-buzz-in-chennai&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;111644935.cms&quot;&gt;report in The Times of India&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, visited Chittaranjan Salai—the residence of CM
Stalin—and then left for a dinner meeting on the ECR, before returning home the same
night.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RTI requests by Arappor Iyakkam to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;dipr.tn.gov.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;DIPR&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, gave a
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pbs.twimg.com&#x2F;media&#x2F;GfDsMw3WwAATwKU?format=jpg&amp;amp;name=large&quot;&gt;response that they did not have any information on Adani&#x27;s
visit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
although the Tamil Nadu Police was involved in the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=7Z6FyvphMGs&quot;&gt;security arrangements as
seen in this video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other political parties like the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.thehindu.com&#x2F;news&#x2F;national&#x2F;tamil-nadu&#x2F;cms-son-in-law-sabareesan-met-adani-bjp-state-president-annamalai&#x2F;article68973903.ece&quot;&gt;BJP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;timesofindia.indiatimes.com&#x2F;city&#x2F;chennai&#x2F;ramadoss-demands-stalins-explanation-on-tangedcos-ties-with-adani&#x2F;articleshow&#x2F;115534839.cms&quot;&gt;PMK&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
and the
&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.business-standard.com&#x2F;politics&#x2F;aiadmk-slams-tamil-nadu-cm-stalin-says-he-is-a-pathological-liar-124121100061_1.html&quot;&gt;AIADMK&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;
have caught on to this scandal and have used it to corner the DMK, while they
themselves, do not support any investigations on the Adani Group at the centre.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire Government and Political System seem to benefit from the Adani Group
and are afraid to act against them. In all these, the common man stands to lose
the most.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We feel pained by what we see and want to do something to change
the situation, but do not know what to do.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Democracy, political parties are still at the mercy of elections, votes and
ultimately the people (though there are attempts to weaken this power through
the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;One_Nation,_One_Election&quot;&gt;One Nation, One
Election&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; proposal).
They still fear them more than any Adani, but we fail to raise our voice loud
enough to reach their ears. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;nyaaya.org&#x2F;resource&#x2F;guide-to-lawful-protesting&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Peaceful
protests&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and
demonstrations are the loudest alarm bells, while views, likes and comments on
social media are sweet lullabies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope, I have convinced you to stand with Arappor Iyakkam on January 5, at
Valluvar Kottam and make our voices heard.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RSVP: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;RegisterForAdaniProtestEvent&quot;&gt;Register For Adani Protest Event&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	<entry xml:lang="en">
		<title>Arappor Iyakkam</title>
		<published>2024-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
		<updated>2024-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
		<link rel="alternate" href="https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/arappor-iyakkam/" type="text/html"/>
		<id>https://arunkd13.github.io/blog/arappor-iyakkam/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently started volunteering with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arappor.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Arappor Iyakkam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;,
which is a civil society organization that fights for an accountable government.
I had been following their work for the past 6 to 7 years, and now that I have
some time to spare, I decided to spend at least one day a week volunteering with
them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first activity that I participated was the audit of the tenders that were
given out by the Greater Chennai Corporation for restoring water bodies. These
were for works like deepening the lake or pond and constructing bunds and
pathways around them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well known that, the tenders given to contractors for public works are a
major source of corruption, and it was heartening to see common citizens banding
together to make sure our tax money is not wasted.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked two water bodies viz. Karuppan Kulam and Vairavan Pond, both near
Ambattur. As instructed by the coordinator I visited both the water bodies, took
extensive photographs of the restoration work that was underway and also talked
to a few residents to gather information on when the work carried out and
submitted them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volunteering with them has shown a glimpse of the extensive field work they do
and the effort involved.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One gripe was that I did not receive enough visibility of the overall progress
of the project. There was only one full time employee who coordinated all the
volunteers through WhatsApp. He was clearly overburdened, and I could not expect
him to worry about volunteer engagement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am hoping to see more information on this campaign in the coming months and
see how effective it is.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>
